<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The triumph of love over fortune a pleasant novel / written in French by that great wit of France, M. St. Bremond ; and translated into English by a person of quality.</title>
            <title>Triomphe de l'amour sur le destin. English</title>
            <author>Brémond, Gabriel de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1678</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4357</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1287</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13068007</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13068007</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97088</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29300)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97088)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 409:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The triumph of love over fortune a pleasant novel / written in French by that great wit of France, M. St. Bremond ; and translated into English by a person of quality.</title>
                  <title>Triomphe de l'amour sur le destin. English</title>
                  <author>Brémond, Gabriel de.</author>
                  <author>Person of quality.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 153, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for James Magnes and Richard Bentley ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1678.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Triomphe de l'amour sur le destin.</note>
                  <note>First ed. in English. Cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>"Licensed, October 11, 1677. Ro. L'Estrange"--P. [1] at beginning.</note>
                  <note>Some pages are stained, signature A is missing, p. 30-35, 50, and 53 have faded print in filmed copy. Beginning-p. 25 and 30-55 photographed from British Library copy and inserted at end.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement: [3] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Newberry Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:97088:1"/>
            <p>LICENSED, <hi>RO. L'ESTRANGE,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>October 11. 1677.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97088:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Triumph OF LOVE OVER FORTUNE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Pleaſant Novel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written in</hi> French <hi>by that Great Wit of</hi> France <hi>M.</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Bremond.</p>
            <p>AND <hi>Tranſlated into</hi> Engliſh <hi>by a Perſon of Quality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>James Magnes</hi> and <hi>Richard Bentley,</hi> in <hi>Ruſſel-Street</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> near the <hi>Piazzas.</hi> 1678.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:97088:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97088:2"/>
            <head>The Triumph of Love over Fortune.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Sun had newly paſt the vernal Aequinox, the Earth breath'd Sweets, the Air was mild and temperate, the Face of Heaven ſmil'd, and all the World look'd gay and youthful, when a King of <hi>Spain</hi> (whoſe Name Hiſtory mentions not) accepting readily the tempting invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of that charming ſeaſon, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to take the Country-Air, and pleaſe himſelf with thoſe divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments a ſhort receſs from <hi>Madrid</hi> fairly promis'd him. He was a Prince fam'd for Gallantry and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence; and of his Courtiers who could pretend to either, there was
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97088:3"/>not one he took not with him to <hi>Aranjues;</hi> where, beſides the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure they frequently took in Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they were entertain'd with Balls and Dances, Opera's, Races, Tournaments, and other rare diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements, wherein the Lords and Grandees of his Court wholly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd themſelves to excel each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aranjues</hi> is a Houſe of pleaſure, ſeated moſt deliciouſly, diſtant from <hi>Madrid</hi> a ſhort days journey between that City and <hi>Toledo,</hi> well built and neatly furniſh'd; but neither Furniture too rich, nor Building too Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent for a Palace-Royal and Reſidence of Majeſty. The curious, who tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel as far as <hi>Madrid,</hi> never forget to take a turn to <hi>Aranjues</hi> to view the Walks and Gardens there, as worth their ſight; where the Bowers, the Water-works, the Grottes, the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, Labyrinths, and other Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments entertain them with a plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97088:3"/>verdure; and by the joint fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours of Art and Nature appears a charming Beauty. To compleat all, what can more delight the Eye than the fair Rows of Trees there of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious height, in a Country which, for twenty Leagues about, ſcarce produces thoſe of ordinary growth?</p>
            <p>The King took more delight in that houſe (as fitted more for Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) than his Palaces of <hi>Prad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> del Campo,</hi> and the <hi>Buen Retiro,</hi> ſtanding hard-by the Gates of <hi>Madrid.</hi> The ſplendor he lived in there was attra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive enough to bring thither all the Nobles of his Kingdom, had they wanted inclination to follow him where e're he went: But he was a Prince who, to the height of State and Power, added ſo many charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing qualities of perſonal Excellency, 'twas difficult to judge whether his Subjects love, or duty to him were the greater.</p>
            <p>Never was Reign happier than
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97088:4"/>his. He was a comely Perſon, hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom and witty to admiration; Young, tall, nimble, and capable of all that's brave, or great; of noble inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, worthy the Crown he wore. Thoſe leiſure-hours his glory and cares of State allow'd him, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd in Love and Gallantry: and no Man ever acquitted himſelf bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and came off with more ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> have in all Ages been obſerved much inclin'd to jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie: the Women there are ſlaves to that paſſion, before they know what 'tis to love. Hence it is they are ſuch early Lovers: 'tis natural, eſpecially for Women, to long for that which is forbidden them. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt is with them a certain effect of Reſtraint: and a Husband jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous (though of the moſt honeſt Wife on Earth,) is upon the point of being made what he moſt fears to be.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:97088:4"/>
            <p>In this King's time, the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> had put on a new Face, the courſe of things, at leaſt in matters of gallantry, was wholly alter'd, and Maxims introduc'd (quite contrary to thoſe formerly in vogue, but) in favour of the Gallants: And their Party being ſtrongeſt, the jealous were forced to ſlacken a little the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor and ſtrictneſs of Ancient Cuſtoms to make way for New. The Ladies had free acceſs to all entertainments, and needed not thoſe ſubtil Intrigues, and Multitude of Confidents they formerly us'd to carry on their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours; the Races, the Walks and the Plays, were the ordinary Rendezvous to make and appoint, and ſometimes to compleat and perform Aſſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>What a brave time was this for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Ladies! they think of it to this day with ſorrow 'tis paſt: and declare with indignation that the Name of this King, which thoſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97088:5"/>of his time ſuffer'd to be bury'd in oblivion, deſerv'd to have been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graved in Letters of Gold over the Chamber-Doors of all the gallant Ladies of his Court, and tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Poſterity to be had in perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Veneration.</p>
            <p>Amidſt the pleaſures of <hi>Aranjues,</hi> Love, jealous perhaps to ſee this Prince ſo long free, and not ſenſible of the power of his influence, reſolved to find him imployment by engaging him in an Amour the more difficult to manage, as having in it no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence from Ambition or Fortune to countenance the purſuit: And the truth is, it gave him more trouble than an hundred others he had been engag'd in. This was not an Amour with the Daughter, or Wife of any Grandee of his Kingdom: He had already paſt through all the Degrees of his Nobility; not a Lord in his Court, but by a Wife, a Daughter, or a Kinſwoman was related to the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97088:5"/>King. But the preſent Engagement was more extraordinary, as very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote from any thing of Pomp, or of Grandeur. 'Twas in a Garden, from among the Roſes and Lilles, Love pick'd out a Beauty to charm the King: a Beauty to which <hi>Aran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jues</hi> gave Birth.</p>
            <p>Among the Courtiers (who made it their buſineſs to find every day ſome new divertiſement for the King) one reſolv'd to entertain him with a Shepherd who play'd excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently on the Flute. The King, a great Lover of Muſick, (eſpecially on thoſe Country-Inſtruments) took extreme delight in hearing him play.</p>
            <p>And finding that the Shepherd, beſides his skill in Muſick, had in all his actions an Air and Grace free from any clowniſhneſs, he was ſo taken with him, that he admitted him of his Muſick, and gave him (as the reſt) a Penſion of two hundred Pata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coons a year.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97088:6"/>
            <p>This generous bounty of the King had put another Shepherd into a tranſport of joy, but was received by <hi>Antonine</hi> with a calmneſs and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration which aſtoniſht that Prince, and forc'd him, after a ſtricter exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his Shepherd, now his new Muſician, to ſay, the Body of that plain Shepherd lodg'd a large and noble Soul. Some Lords taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the pleaſure the King took in viewing him, (though they did not comprehend his thoughts of him) told the King, that to perfect the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement, he muſt ſee dance to the Flute, the Gardiner's Daughter of <hi>Aranjues,</hi> the prettieſt Maid of all the Neighbourhood: The King im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately long'd to ſee her, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded ſhe ſhould come before him.</p>
            <p>She came dreſt like a Nymph: and <hi>Antonine</hi> ſcarce began to play on his Flute, but ſhe fell a-dancing; and with that grace, that cadence, thoſe geſtures ſo proper and ſo ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97088:6"/>that ſhe charm'd the whole Court. She was a Girl about fifteen years of age, having alittle of the Country Meen, and Air, but nothing ruſtick, and a very pleaſing Face.</p>
            <p>The King (none of the moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſible) firſt felt the force of her charms; every ſtep ſhe made, each geſture, every action of the little Country-Laſs were ſo many Magick Spells to inchant this Prince. He felt his heart ſeiz'd with an unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countable ſudden joy, as ſhe drew near him in dancing, or look'd upon him; and 'twas not in his power to forbear, once or twice, diſcovering his Paſſion by Exclamations the whole Court took notice of.</p>
            <p>This was the only pleaſure he took all that day; apleaſure that troubled all the reſt they would have diverted him with at <hi>Aranjues.</hi> The little Maid was ſcarce withdrawn with the Shepherd, but the King fell into a deep melancholy, which put him
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97088:7"/>wholly out of humour. He had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd a familiarity betwixt 'em, which, though uſual among Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-People, ſeem'd to trouble him though he knew not why. The La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies he had moſt eſteem for endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to divert him, but in vain; for he ſpent the reſt of the day in walking alone, to enjoy the pleaſure of his new Idea's.</p>
            <p>He was reſtleſs all night, and could not ſleep, he thought a thouſand times of the little Country-Girl, and indeed could think of nothing elſe; he fancy'd her ſo beautiful and char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, ſo innocent, ſo Country-like, that his imaginations finiſh'd the work Love had but begun.</p>
            <p>The Sun had ſcarce appear'd in his Chamber, but he got up; and being dreſt, went a walking in the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, where he ſent for the Shepherd to furniſh himſelf with a pretence for ſeeing the Girl, whom he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently gave order for. <hi>Antonine</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:97088:7"/>play'd on the Flute, the Girl danced the king charmed anew with new graces he fancy'd he diſcover'd every moment in her, was more and more affected, and, in a word, deeply in love with her. No ſooner had this Paſſion taken poſſeſſion of his heart, but his jealouſie of the Shepherd in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creas'd. He ſaw the Girl ſmile on him, and obſerv'd a tenderneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt in every look ſhe gave him; and that ſhe took pleaſure in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to him: and that the Shepherd diſcover'd ſome little complaiſances of a Lover, both when he play'd, and when he came near her, which, convinc'd the King there was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them a correſpondence of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. This vext the King at heart, and the more becauſe his paſſion was ſo new he durſt not yet reveal it: At laſt, unable to endure the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his own impatience, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to be longer witneſs of the Shepherd's happineſs to which he
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97088:8"/>thought himſelf contributary, he ſent away the Gardiner's Daughter, but kept the Shepherd with him. He continued walking without ſpeaking a word to any but Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> Marqueſs <hi>de Las Tarrillas</hi> his Confident and Favourite, to whom he reveal'd the ſecret of his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, with expreſſions and ſighs which ſufficiently evidenc'd he had never been ſo deep in Love. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs having obſerv'd the King had till then been taken only with Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties eminent for Birth and Merit, was ſurpris'd to ſee him on the ſudden fall ſo low. He was a dextrous Courtier, a great Maſter of the Art of pleaſing Princes; but in ſpight of all his policy and complaiſance for his King, he could not forbear telling him (with that liberty which brought him into favour) that an Engagement, that ſo ill became his Quality and Character, would occaſion much diſcourſe in a Country naturally too
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97088:8"/>ſatyrical: <q>There are, Sir, adds he, in your Court more accompliſh'd Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, more Noble and Illuſtrious, whoſe charms will not ſtain the ſplendor of your affection.</q>
               <q>Yes, replys the King, there are Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties who love my Quality, not me; whoſe kindneſs terminates in themſelves, who pretend a paſſion for me, only to ſerve their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, and raiſe their fortunes. Who conſent to my deſires out of hopes to be advanc'd by the affection of a King: Take theſe hopes away, and aſſure your ſelf of a repulſe. Ah, Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> 'tis a miſery for a delicate and tender Lover not to know whether he ows his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts to Merit, or to Fortune; or at leaſt whether they are not gain'd more by what appears without, than what moves within.</q>
               <q>But, Sir, ſaid Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> conſider 'tis a Gardiner's Daughter.</q>
               <q>Yes, a Gardiner's Daughter, replys the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97088:9"/>King; and pray, adds he in ſome heat, what were ſuch and ſuch, before I made them what they are? And how many Grandees are there this day at Court who owe their riſe to Love; and had it not been for the gallantries of my Anceſtors, had perhaps been leſs than the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of this charming Maid. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with your ſelf what pleaſure it will be to me to gain the love of that innocent Girl, who peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture knows not what Love is, till I teach her; who deſires not Riches or Titles; whoſe kindneſs will be an effect of my paſſion, and her affection a Creature of mine.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> finding by this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe 'twould be in vain to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour diverting the King from a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion he had ſo deeply eſpous'd, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd himſelf wholly (as is uſual with thoſe of his Character) to pleaſe him in ſerving his paſſion, and preſerve himſelf the honour of his Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97088:9"/>telling him, he needed only to have the Gardiner ſpoken to, who would think himſelf too much ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured that his Majeſty ſhould vouchſafe his Daughter a look. <q>Yes, replys the King; and ſhould the Father be for me and deliver me his Daughter, think you that Sacrifice would ſatisfie my paſſion? No, no, Don <hi>Auguſtin;</hi> the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on I have for that amiable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not ſuch as you imagine, which a bare fruition may ſatisfie, I muſt have her affection, or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and cannot expect any reſt till I have gained her heart. I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the Enterprize appears diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult to take a Place by formal At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taques, where Art, Wit, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps Merit will be uſeleſs: but this, if I ſucceed, will render the Conqueſt more worthy my affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and heighten the pleaſure of having obtain'd my deſire. You ſpeak of Beauty, adds he, having
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97088:10"/>walked ſome paces without ſaying a word, is there any thing ſo pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in all the Court? and had you obſerv'd her ſtature, her parts, her meen, the grace attends all ſhe ſays, all ſhe does, durſt you have told me there is any thing ſo charming in the World? Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine her better, view her more ſtrictly, and you will ſee there is not a finer Girl under Heaven. She has not the breeding of our Ladies, but is that a fault? is not pure Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture more amiable?</q>
            </p>
            <p>After a diſcourſe ſo full of Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Love, which the Marqueſs thought not fit to contradict, the King asked who the Gardiner was, and whom the Shepherd belong'd to. The Marqueſs being ignorant of both, could not give any ſatisfactory account; but had order to inform himſelf particularly where the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner dwelt, what Family he had, and how deſcended; and to take it
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97088:10"/>into his ſpecial protection and care: and to enquire who the Shepherd was, and whether he viſited the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner's Daughter.</p>
            <p>A Maſter is never ſerved with more cheerfulneſs than in his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, as the beſt Scene for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to play his own Game in, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially having hopes effectually to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer the Maſter's expectation, as Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> had. He ſent that ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day in ſearch of <hi>Dorothy</hi>'s Father, and after ſeveral diſcourſes about his Family, let him know he was in a fair way to come to as good fortune as a Man of his condition could wiſh. He ask'd him if he knew <hi>Antonine;</hi> and was fully inform'd by the Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner concerning that Shepherd: then he bid him have a care of his Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whom he was to look upon as the Author of his good fortune, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving further light whether the Marqueſs, or any other were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in the advice. This was ſo
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97088:11"/>managed by order from the King: And the Expreſſions (like infallible Oracles) coming from the Mouth of the Marqueſs <hi>de las Torrillas,</hi> whoſe Countenance was ſufficient to raiſe the fortune of the greateſt Subject of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſo tranſported the Good Man that he knew not how to make his acknowledgment for joy. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, to make good his words by ſuitable effects, put into his hand a Purſe of an hundred Piſtols, the moſt certain confirmation he could poſſibly have given the Gardiner of the News he had told him. He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd home, ſo fully aſſur'd by what he had in his hand, of the favourable influence of his Stars, that he thought himſelf the happieſt, if not the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Man upon Earth.</p>
            <p>The Favourite having executed his Commiſſion, like a worthy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, goes to give his Maſter an account; and acquainting him with the Particulars of the Gardiner's Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97088:11"/>told him, he was fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd he was a very honeſt Man, who lived very privately, not admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting into his Houſe any one might bring a ſcandal upon him: And that his Daughter <hi>Dorothy</hi> had the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of a Maid ſo free from intrigue that ſhe had never been ſuſpected to have been engag'd in one.
<q>And what of <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſays the King?</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonine,</hi> Sir, ſays the Marqueſs, is the Son of a rich Shepherd near <hi>Tolledo,</hi> who was recommended to the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diner, and lodges at his Houſe.</q>
               <q>
                  <hi>Antonine,</hi> replys the King ſighing, doth he Lodge at <hi>Dorothy</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's?</q>
               <q>Yes, Sir, ſaid the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, very much ſurpriz'd to ſee how the King received the News of it; but I believe there's no cauſe to fear him.</q>
               <q>More cauſe, replys the King, more a great deal than you think.</q>
               <q>What, a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, anſwers the Marqueſs?</q>
               <q>Yes, a Shepherd, ſays the King;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97088:12"/>a Shepherd who hath all the good qualities requiſite to gain the love of a Shepherdeſs. Had you view'd him with the Eyes of a Lover, you would have quickly diſcovered what 'tis to be ſuch a Shepherd. Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> adds he, no Rival is contemptible; to ſlight him, is to loſe all.</q>
               <q>But, Sir, ſays the Marqueſs, you are his Maſter, and may rid your hands of him when you pleaſe: Theſe ſort of Lovers have not ſo ſtrong inclinations as we. Give him but a better Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment in another place than he hath here, he'll yield up his Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herdeſs to you, and quit all his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions to her.</q>
               <q>You think ſo, replys the King, but I do not. But ſhould I comply with my affection in taking your advice, what will the World ſay of my removing the Shepherd after the favour I have ſhew'd him? will they not ſay I have baniſh'd him? And the Wits,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97088:12"/>who claim a ſoveraign jurisdiction to cenſure all actions, when they ſee me court this Girl; will they not ſay preſently, I was jealous of <hi>Antonine?</hi> No, no, I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd in Reputation to let him ſtay with her at the peril of having my paſſion made publick by removal of him: if he be a profeſt Lover of her, 'tis my part to endeavour gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her from him. But I muſt firſt know how far he is advanc'd, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhe is pleas'd with his addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or barely permits them, or loves him in good earneſt. Theſe Myſteries are never well diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but by thoſe who have been in Love; a meer Confident cannot penetrate them: Therefore get two Suits made me after the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-Faſhion; and let them be brought me to-morrow at my ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing: I will go in Perſon to the Gardiner's, to obſerve <hi>Dorothy</hi> and <hi>Antonine.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97088:13"/>
            <p>Any Man but the Marqueſs would have boggled, and been ſcandaliz'd at a deſign ſo contrary to the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gravity, and unſuitable to Majeſty; but he was ſo well acquainted with the Gallantries of his Prince, and ſo verſt in the management of them for the King, who loved adventures and diſguiſes, that he was ready to fall a laughing at the Frolick: but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting they had no acquaintance, nor correſpondence at the Gardiner's, he apprehended ſome miſchance which might be laid to his charge. He repreſented it to the King as he carried him the Habits on the Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, telling him he expos'd the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of his Perſon to affront, by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturing diſguis'd into a Man's Houſe he was not acquainted with. The King who lov'd not to be croſs'd, made him a ſhort anſwer, that in matters of Love he expected from a Perſon of his Character a great deal of Complaiſance, but no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97088:13"/>Counſel; and that the advice he commonly took in thoſe Caſes, was only ſuch as his affection ſuggeſted him. He put on one of thoſe Suits, and the Marqueſs having taken the other, they went down a privy Stair which brought them to a Walk in the Garden; where they were no ſooner entred, but they ſaw <hi>Dorothy</hi> picking Flowers. The jealous Prince, raviſh'd with joy, made ſigns to Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> to follow him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out noiſe; and went with him into the Muſes Bower, at the corner of the Walk, where they hid themſelves from her. <q>Tis an excellent op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, ſays the King to his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident, we muſt follow her to ſee who the Noſegay is made for.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The patience of the Monarch, on this occaſion, was admirable; but muſt be conſidered as an effect of his Love. At laſt <hi>Dorothy</hi> goes out, taking the way of the Long Walks, to the aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of the Parties concern'd,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97088:14"/>eſpecially the Amorous Prince, who more curious than ever to know whither ſhe went, follow'd her with no ſmall perplexity and agitation of heart. It was not long but he might gueſs at her deſign; for they were ſcarce paſt the ſecond Walk but they heard <hi>Antonine</hi>'s Flute, which the King thought not half ſo ſweet then as formerly. He looked twice or thrice on Don <hi>Auguſtin</hi> without ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a word; but not able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal his jealouſie longer, <q>You ſee now, ſays he, whether I have not reaſon enough to fear this Rival. Ah, Don <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> my Curioſity is like to coſt me dear: but 'tis no matter, let's go and ſee all.</q> They went beſide the Walks to avoid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeen by her: at laſt they ſaw <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> making up to <hi>Antonine,</hi> and preſenting him with the Noſegay; which the Shepherd receiving with actions full of Love, and of Joy, took her by the hand, which ſhe permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97088:14"/>him to kiſs; a great Favour in <hi>Spain,</hi> and ſignifies ſomething more. This vext the Jealous King at the heart, to that degree of Impatience he was juſt making up to them. But <hi>Dorothy</hi> having not ſtay'd a moment longer with the Shepherd, the King advanced no further, but returned towards the Palace.</p>
            <p>He was penſive and melancholy, and paſt thoſe ſhady Walks muſing of the happineſs of a Shepherd, which a King was forced to envy. He ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted the Marqueſs with his thoughts; the Marqueſs told him, the beſt way to quiet his Spirits was to ſend away the Shepherd.
<q>But who can aſſure me, replies the King, that by removing him from <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi>'s Perſon, I ſhall remove him from her affection. A months ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, Sir, ſays the Marqueſs, will aſſure you of it. Abſence, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers the King, too frequently ſtrengthens affection; and I am not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97088:15"/>now to learn oppoſition heightens Love. But I am content for the pleaſure of the Experiment, to try the means you propoſe. Give him a Place at <hi>Buen Retiro,</hi> and let him be ſent away this day.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Auſtin</hi> undertook the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. And having put off his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe, went about <hi>Antonine</hi>'s Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, which was preſently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd. The Office they gave him was to be Porter of his Majeſty's Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace of <hi>Buen Retiro,</hi> as the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for a young Man of his Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter. They who carried him the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for it, made him underſtand it as an effect of the King's Bounty to him; though he did not take it ſo, but anſwered thoſe who congratula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his good Fortune, that <q>He knew not what belonged to being a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that the King might honour an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other with the Imployment, who might deſerve and perform it bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. As for him, he had kept ſheep
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97088:15"/>all his Life, and would do nothing elſe.</q> They preſt him however to undertake the Imploy; but the King having ordered no violence ſhould be offered him, and the Shepherd having deſired to ſpeak with the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ſhould be ſent away, they let him go.</p>
            <p>The Shepherd went to the King, fell down at his feet, and with all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility begg'd of him not to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>load and oppreſs him with his Boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, but permit him to continue (as he had found him) a Shepherd; and not force him to quit a Condition he had devoted his Life to, and preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red before all others, aſſuring His Majeſty he was content, he was ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with what he had, and envy'd no Man. The King as ſoon as he perceiv'd <hi>Antonine</hi> come towards him, fell a-laughing; but when he heard him ſpeak, he ſigh'd; not for Jealouſie, but for very trouble it was not in his power to be ſo happy as the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97088:16"/>Shepherd. How happy, thinks he, is this Shepherd, to have all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires either of Love or Fortune? As he made theſe Reflections, he view'd him from top to toe. And admiring a young Man of that Condition ſhould have ſentiments ſo extraordinary, he had judged him to be quite other than he appear'd, but that he lookt upon't as (an effect though) a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Love. This Prince had a Soul too Noble and Generous, not to make his Jealouſie vail to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of <hi>Antonine;</hi> ſo that he could not prevail with himſelf to ſend him away. He called for <hi>Dorothy,</hi> and the better to penetrate the ſecrets of her heart, told her, She might now take her Leave of <hi>Antonine,</hi> for he was ſending him away to <hi>Buen Retiro,</hi> where he had buſineſs for him, and had given him a good Imployment. The poor Innocent was thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruck at this; her Blood fluſh'd into her face to compleat the Embelliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97088:16"/>of the moſt Charming Beauty on Earth: She ſuddenly made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, She was ſure <hi>Antonine</hi> would not accept of the Employment, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had promis'd her he would die rather than part with her. <q>But I would have him go thither, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes the King; it will be his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, and the making of his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; And will you be againſt it?</q> 
               <q>No, Sir, ſayes ſhe; but I humbly beſeech your Majeſty to command my Father to let me go along with him to look to the Garden there.</q> 
               <q>You love the Shepherd then I ſee, ſayes the King:</q> And <hi>Dorothy</hi> making him no anſwer, he roſe; and not able to endure longer ſo tormenting a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, left her with <hi>Antonine.</hi> The Marqueſs (who was preſent there) follow'd the King, admiring no leſs the patience of his Prince, than charm'd at the paſſion of the two Countrey-Lovers. <q>Well, <hi>Don Auſtin,</hi> ſayes the King to him, when they
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97088:17"/>got a little out of the Crowd, was ever Lover ſo unfortunate as I? Here is a Rival, and a Rival belov'd. I muſt of neceſſity either conquer my paſſion, or ſend him packing. Yet ſuch is my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I cannot do the one or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</q> The Favourite complying with the humor of his Maſter, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, 'Twas in truth ſomething rare to ſee a Prince in Love (as he was) expreſs ſo much Goodneſs and Favour for a Shepherd, who ſtood in his way, and might croſs his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns: But that ſometimes particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Engagements require particular Conduct. <q>Hitherto, Sir, adds he, you have lov'd like a King: variety is pleaſant, and to change ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times is very delightful. Perhaps you may find pleaſure in deveſting your ſelf of Majeſty, and addreſſing your ſelf to a Countrey-Girl, after the manner of thoſe of her Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter who court her.</q> The King was
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97088:17"/>willing to do it; and to let the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs ſee how kindly he took the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verture, he told him, That in Love-Policy the firſt thing a Lover is to do, is to accommodate himſelf to the Condition and humor of his Miſtreſs: And that thoſe Charming bonds of Sympathy, which link'd hearts into ſo cloſe an union, had their beginning from thence. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, they concluded <hi>Dorothy</hi> ſhould be taken from her Parents, and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with ſome Lady of the Court, where the King might ſee her with more convenience and leſs noiſe.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs willing to have the honour of managing the Intrigue, and loth any other ſhould pretend to the Advantage he promis'd him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from it, propoſed to the King, That <hi>Dorothy</hi> ſhould be placed with the Marchioneſs his Wife; her Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment being next the King's, (who was every day there) and the moſt convenient of any in the Palace.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97088:18"/>The King had thought of it before; but the Marchioneſs, though young and handſom, made great profeſſion of Vertue, and ſtood much upon her Honour, which made the King fear ſhe would be hardly induc'd to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept a ſhare in that Confidence he was willing to repoſe in her. No man knew her better than the King, having been formerly in love with her, though without any conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſucceſs; which had not a little contributed to the haughtineſs of this Lady, and gain'd her the Repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of an Extraordinary Merit. So rare are the Examples of Beauties whoſe Vertue is proof againſt the Paſſions of Kings: we muſt ſeek them in former Ages. In our days faults committed with Princes, are ſo far from being reputed crimes, that the offenders triumph in their weakneſs, and make their Infirmity their Glory.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs <hi>de las Torillas</hi> might have pretended to the honour
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97088:18"/>of the Vertuous Ladies of Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Times, and the King after the experience he had of her Vertue, had reaſon to fear ſhe would not be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with the Employment. But the Marqueſs, the moſt zealous of Favo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites to do a Maſter ſervice, had that confidence in the kindneſs his Lady had for him, and made the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve ſo much of the power he had over her, that this Prince, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd it as much at leaſt as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, gave him leave to propoſe it to his Lady.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs took his time. Man and Wife can gueſs pretty near the good hour they may obtain what they deſire of one another. <hi>Don Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> was of opinion the Lucky mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was much about the time of firſt waking in the morning. After ſome little endearments and careſſes, for prologue to the enſuing diſcourſe, he fell a-talking of Love; how it takes us when we leaſt think on't,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97088:19"/>and ſometimes by objects that little deſerv'd it: that this had happen'd to the King, whoſe affection had ſtoop'd ſo low as the Gardiner's pret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Daughter. That in truth it appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a blemiſh to his Honour, which till now had not permitted him to place his affection on any object unworthy it. But that Love is Blind, and Kings are Men as well as others. He paſt then to the obligations they were under to their Prince, who daily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow'd new Favours upon them: And when he came to the point of acquainting her with the King's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have the Gardiner's Daughter with her, he endeavour'd to gild over the propoſal with the advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges it would bring them, to have in their Family a young Innocent thing who would be at their diſpoſe; and by the paſſion the King had for her, was like to be one of the greateſt La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies at Court, and improve by that means their Credit and Favour. The
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97088:19"/>haughty Marchioneſs had not the patience to let him finiſh a diſcourſe ſo injurious to the Glory ſhe pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to; but rejecting all that fair ſhew of Honour and Fortune to be pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chas'd on ſuch ſhameful conditions, ſhe told him, He was a dirty and pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful Fellow to undertake a buſineſs of this nature, and but think a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of her Quality and Vertue could act ſo baſe and unworthy a part. This confounded <hi>Don Auſtin,</hi> and had utterly defeated him, but that the King, who could not ſleep, came in to his aid. He was impatient to know the anſwer of the Marchioneſs, and entring her Chamber, found her very angry, and little diſpos'd to grant his requeſt. She gave him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt the ſame Language ſhe had given <hi>Don Auſtin,</hi> but temper'd with the Civility and reſpects due to Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty: But as ſhe complain'd what ſmall value he had for her, after ſo many reaſons to eſteem her, ſhe added
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97088:20"/>he was Maſter there, and might di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſe as he pleas'd of her Apartment; but ſhe hop'd he would give her leave to retire, that he might have the more room, and ſhe not incommode him. The King who never quitted a deſign he had eſpous'd, heard her without the leaſt interruption. And when ſhe had done, he ſpoke her ſo fair, and gave her ſuch ſmooth and inſinuating Language, that he made her believe it would not reflect upon her Honour to grant him his deſire. In a word, he obtain'd her conſent to take <hi>Dorothy</hi> for one of her Maids, and promis'd her ſhe ſhould be no further concern'd.</p>
            <p>The King triumphing for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt he had gain'd over the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs, the moſt haughty and tender of her Honour of all the Ladies of his Court, told the Marqueſs, He muſt go ſpeak to <hi>Dorothy</hi>'s Father. The Gardiner brought his Daughter to <hi>Don Auſtin;</hi> and thought himſelf ſo
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97088:20"/>much oblig'd for the Preſent of the hundred Piſtoles, that he would in acknowledgment have brought him his Wife had he deſir'd it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonine</hi> was then tending his Sheep, and, at his return home, ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently ſurpriz'd not to find <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> there, and to hear ſhe was gone to wait on the Marchioneſs <hi>de las To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillas,</hi> he ſtay'd not a moment at the Gardiner's, but would go learn of <hi>Dorothy</hi> what made that Lady take her into her Family. He had diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd it was the Marqueſs would have honoured him with the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of Porter of <hi>Buen Retiro;</hi> and knowing he was ſeldom guilty of too much generoſity, nor reputed very obliging, he ſuſpected him for the favour he would have done him. And now, thinks he, the King hath the goodneſs to allow me to ſtay here, the Marqueſs muſt prefer <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> to wait upon his Lady?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonine,</hi> whoſe Wit (as well as
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97088:21"/>Birth) was too high for the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Shepherd, though he wore the habit, preſently diſcover'd there was deſign in the Buſineſs: That the love he had for that Maid, and the kindneſs ſhe expreſt for him had been taken notice of: And ſome were grown jealous of him. But <hi>Don Auſtin</hi> was the Man he ſuſpected, having no thought the King was concern'd. <hi>Antonine</hi> goes to Court, enters the Marchioneſs Apartment, and making uſe of that liberty the King's Favour allow'd him, he runs up and down, and at laſt finds his Miſtriſs, walking alone in a Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where the Marqueſs had newly left her. He takes her aſide, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcarce able to ſpeak for the trouble he was in, <q>
                  <hi>Dorothy,</hi> ſays he, you know I love you, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may believe none more gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d than my ſelf for your good Fortune in being plac'd with the Marchioneſs <hi>de las Torillas.</hi> You will never have
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97088:21"/>a Fortune anſwerable to your merit and my wiſhes: But, to deal plainly with you, this deſign of taking you from your Father's bodes me no good. I am too ſenſible of it; I will not tell you why, nor how, for I cannot if I would: but there is ſomething in it makes me terribly afraid. Nor that I can think you will change your affection with your Fortune: And that being made higher than you were, you will ſlight a Shepherd, who ſlights all for you. I have a better opinion of your Kindneſs and Conſtancy, and know you better principl'd than to give me cauſe to ſuſpect you of any thing ſo mean. But, <hi>Dorothy,</hi> the Court is a dangerous place for a young thing as you are, and you quit the Innocence of our Woods to follow the Court. You are here in a Houſe, where doubtleſs I cannot have the ſame liberty as at your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther's; nor ſee you but in the croud,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97088:22"/>nor ſpeak with you but before wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: What a torment will this be to a Shepherd that loves you as I do? who deſire to ſee you every moment, and have always ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſay to you.</q> To theſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous reaſons he added a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand conſiderations, which made great impreſſion on the young Maid, as ſpoken by one who had the gift of perſwading her what ever he pleas'd. She was juſt going back with him to her Father's, but <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> told her ſhe muſt not be too haſty. And as he was upon acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her with the meaſures ſhe ſhould obſerve, word was brought her the King would ſpeak with her, and ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for her in the Marchioneſs's Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. <hi>Antonine,</hi> who thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo much in the King's Favour, that he might without offence bear <hi>Dorothy</hi> company, was willing to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low her, as well to make an end of what he had to ſay to her, as to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97088:22"/>the curioſity he had to know what the King would have with her. They came to the Marchioneſs's Chamber, where they found only <hi>Don Auſtin</hi> and his Lady, which was no ſmall help to make the Shepherd believe his firſt ſuſpicions were not ill-grounded, That the Marqueſs had a mind to <hi>Dorothy,</hi> and would have got rid of him by ſending him to <hi>Buen Retiro,</hi> and had plac'd her with his Lady, on no other deſign but to part him and <hi>Dorothy;</hi> and to make the eaſier prey of her Innocence, us'd the King's Name and Authority againſt him and her. To compleat his trouble, and convince him throughly of the misfortune he dreaded, they were ſcarce entred the Chamber, but the Marqueſs took <hi>Dorothy</hi> by the hand, and led her in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another Room where the King ſtay'd for her, unſeen by <hi>Antonine</hi> who was left alone with the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs. This Lady obſerving the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97088:23"/>countenance of the Shepherd, fell a-laughing to ſee him look ſo pale and wan at his Miſtriſs being taken from him. And to prevent the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicion of being party to the deſign, ſhe reſolved to divertiſe her ſelf with diſcourſing of it; and to clear her Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation ſhe came up to a window where <hi>Antonine</hi> was, and ask'd him ſmiling, how he durſt truſt <hi>Dorothy</hi> with the Marqueſs? <q>I know not, Madam, anſwers he, but believe I muſt take my meaſures in that particular from you, who are e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually concern'd, and (I perſwade my ſelf,) have power enough to prevent any thing of that nature you had reaſon to fear.</q> The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs ſurpriz'd at the anſwer, would try a little further, telling him <hi>Don Auſtin</hi> was Maſter there, and his will was a law to her. <q>I may, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes the Shepherd, ſay as much of <hi>Dorothy,</hi> and with a great deal more reaſon: For I have not any right
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97088:23"/>over her, nor is ſhe oblig'd to give me an account of her actions.</q> 
               <q>But you love her, anſwers the Lady, and Lovers have great rights to their Miſtreſſs.</q> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Don Auſtin,</hi> Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes <hi>Antonine,</hi> is your Husband, and Marriage hath higher rights than Love can pretend to.</q> The Marchioneſs, charmed with theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parties ſo much above the capacity of a Shepherd, look'd upon him with admiration, viewing him a pretty while without ſaying a word. But to bring him in play again: <q>
                  <hi>Don Auſtin,</hi> ſayes ſhe, has found a pretty young Girl he likes better than me, and if he loves her, muſt I take it ill?</q> 
               <q>No, Madam, anſwers <hi>Antonine,</hi> if you love him not: But I who love this Girl with an unparallel'd paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſhould, I confeſs, be at my Wit's end to ſee another partake with me the happineſs of being lov'd by her.</q> 
               <q>You are jealous then, <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſayes the Lady not able to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97088:24"/>forbear laughing.</q> 
               <q>I really am ſo, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, anſwers he, not that I think I have any reaſon for't on this occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but that in truth I cannot for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear it on any: And ſhould <hi>Don Auſtin</hi> deſign no more than diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſement and do all this in jeſt, as I am perſwaded he does, yet is he guilty of the higheſt Cruelty ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, in tormenting a poor Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd who hath no pleaſure of Life but the Love of his Shepherdeſs, wherein <hi>Don Auſtin</hi> gives us di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance without any reaſon.</q> The more the Marchioneſs heard <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> ſpeak, the more willing ſhe was to give him occaſion of ſpeaking. She had heard ſay he was very gentile in his Expreſſions, and had a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar grace in ſpeaking, which was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported the reaſon of the Kings loving him as he did; but ſhe would never have believ'd he had the Wit ſhe perceiv'd in him, his diſcourſe having more than ſurpriz'd her.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:97088:24"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Don Auſtin</hi> coming out of the King's Chamber, took his Lady aſide, praying her to ſend away the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd; for if the King found him there, he would think ſhe had kept him with her of purpoſe to croſs his deſigns. <hi>Antonine</hi> ſeeing the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs come out, thought <hi>Dorothy</hi> was alone, and asked the Lady whether he might not be allow'd to ſee her. She told him, No; And that, if he might, ſhe would not adviſe him to'r. <q>It ſeems then, Madam, ſayes <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine, Don Auſtin</hi> hath forbid it, and came in for that purpoſe, being jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous I would endeavour it; and you are willing to comply with him.</q> 
               <q>No, no, anſwers ſhe ready to burſt with laughing, I'le ſecure you from <hi>Don Auſtin.</hi> He's not the Man y' are to fear: But 'tis enough, <hi>Antonine,</hi> withdraw.</q> 
               <q>What ſay you, Madam, you will ſecure me from the Marqueſs, and would have me withdraw: Can I be ſo unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97088:25"/>(addes he with a lamentable tone,) to have any other to fear?</q> 
               <q>I know not, anſwers ſhe, but ſhould it fall out ſo, as poſſible it may, you muſt be chearful as you can: 'Tis no news for Lovers to have Rivals, and you may have a Rival may be more for your advantage than misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune.</q> The Marchioneſs let fall theſe laſt words out of negligence and meer careleſsneſs, to manage (as ſhe might) an affair which procur'd at once her vexation and her ſcorn. Theſe haughty Ladies who glory in loving no body, and not admitting love from any, are jealous of all the World, when others are jealous on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of thoſe they love. The Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd fix'd his Eye on her awhile, as if he would have read in her Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance the truth of what ſhe had ſaid. <q>More for my advantage, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam! replyes he, Can it be for my advantage to be robb'd of all I love in the World? The more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97088:25"/>the Rival, the greater the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune; and I ſhould be very ſorry he ſhould prove ſuch as you ſay. Oh Heavens! cryes he, not giving her time to anſwer, ſhould he be the Man I imagin! and ſhould I have been born to ſo much miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune!</q> He pronounced theſe words with ſo vehement action, and ſo loud a voice, the Lady was afraid the King had heard him; and that ſhe might be charg'd with having ſpoken too much, the Shepherd hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fully diſcover'd what ſhe thought ſhe had not half told him. She took him by the hand, and mov'd with the tears ſhe ſaw him ſhed, bid him (with an air of Complaiſance) trouble himſelf no further, but come again, and he ſhould ſpeak with <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> who could better inform him. <q>Ah! Madam, anſwers he, I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, I know too much from you.</q>
            </p>
            <p>With that he went out ſo oppreſt with grief he was ſcarce able to ſtand:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97088:26"/>The Marchioneſs was troubl'd to ſee him gone, becauſe ſhe had not given him more comfort at parting; but ſhe was ſo aſtoniſht at what ſhe had heard that ſhe could hardly believe her ſenſes. She had not only never ſeen a Shepherd who could diſcourſe as he had done, but never known any ſo tender a Lover. She could do no other all day than think with what grace and what tranſports he expreſt his paſſion: And ſhe obſerv'd in his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents ſomething ſo noble, ſo rare and ſo moving, that without being guilty of downright inhumanity, ſhe thought it impoſſible not to be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted with them. But by perſwading her ſelf of this truth, ſhe found her heart unquiet, and did nothing but ſigh all the night long. She ſaw not the conſequence of it, or at leaſt would not ſee it. She who had the haughtineſs and height of Spirit to deſpiſe and reject the addreſſes of a Crown'd Head, could not fancy her
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97088:26"/>ſelf capable of the weakneſs to make account of a poor Shepherd. She had indeed pitty'd his tears, but ſhe thought that was all.</p>
            <p>The King the hotteſt Lover in the World, being never at eaſe but when <hi>Dorothy</hi> was in ſight, yet unwilling notice ſhould be taken of his vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent inclinations for her, gave order for ſome days all the Divertiſements of the Court ſhould be in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs's Apartment, where very few had entrance; and of thoſe few who were admitted, poor <hi>Antonine</hi> could never make one, though he endeavour'd to get in all the wayes in his power. This troubled him the more, as having not been able to reſt day or night ſince his laſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe with the Marchioneſs, nor ever likely to be at eaſe, till he could ſpeak with his Miſtreſs.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs who would have been very glad to ſee him, admiring he was not come to her for many
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97088:27"/>days, knew not what to think on't. She ſpy'd him one morning walking under her windows, and having made ſigns to him to come up pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, gave order to an old Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, her Confident, to let him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her Chamber as privately as poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible. <q>
                  <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſays the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, methinks of a Lover ſo paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate as you, y'are ſoon comfort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the loſs of your Miſtreſs.</q> 
               <q>I cannot yet think her altogether loſt, Madam, anſwers he, nor gueſs at the reaſon they were ſo cruel to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny me the favour of ſeeing her.</q> 
               <q>You muſt look you out another Miſtreſs, <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſays the Lady, and ſuch a Shepherd as you are may have your choice.</q> 
               <q>Look out ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Madam, replyes <hi>Antonine,</hi> with a tone that ſufficiently eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced his grief and ſurprize, ſhe muſt be firſt falſe to me, and I very clearly convinc'd of it: Beſides, I know not whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> after all I ſhould not rather
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97088:27"/>chooſe ceaſing to live than to love her. But, Madam, adds he like a Man in afright, is it from her you give me this advice; and has ſhe no more mind to me?</q> 
               <q>I do not ſay ſo, anſwers the Lady, I believe <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> loves you: But 'twere better for you to think of another in time, and I tell it you as a Friend.</q> 
               <q>As long as <hi>Dorothy</hi> loves me, replyes the Shepherd, 'twill be impoſſible for me to change. And did you but know what 'tis for a Lover like me to quit his Miſtreſs, you are too generous, Madam, to adviſe me to't: But if <hi>Dorothy,</hi> adds he in a very preſſing and curious manner, be not falſe to me, why ſhould I quit her, Madam, unleſs you take it ill I ſhould make love to her in your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily.</q> 
               <q>No, <hi>Antonine,</hi> anſwers the Lady, you are too expert and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreet a Lover to be found fault with for making Love: I will give you no trouble in't. But—</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:97088:28"/>
            <p>She ſtopt there. <q>Ah! Madam, ſays the Shepherd, ſeeing her make a stop, what torment have you put me to for three or four days, that you have left me in doubt whom I am to fear!</q> The Marchioneſs bid him come again at nine a clock at night, when the King went to Councel, and ſhe would let him ſee <hi>Dorothy,</hi> who would tell him what ſhe was loath to let him know, being very unwilling to be the firſt ſhould give him ſo ill news.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonine</hi> content with this hope, though rack'd with ſuſpicion, return<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed home to wait with impatience the hour was aſſign'd him.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs was more charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed than ever with the merit of the Shepherd. She found in him the Character of ſo tender and paſſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate a Lover, ſhe confeſt no heart could be ſo inſenſible not to be affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him. And for her part, her haughtineſs in ſlighting Love, muſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97088:28"/>own an abligation to the Court for producing no Lovers, but what were corrupt: And ſhe doubted now and then, whether it were not pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in a Lady of her Quality and Honour, to love a Shepherd as <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonine.</hi> Theſe doubts and Reflecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were ſo ſtrong and ſo piercing, her heart which at firſt felt only the point of them, found it ſelf at length very deeply wounded: But ſhe would not yet complain of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the wound, though dnagerous, had ſomething of pleaſure in't which charm'd away the pain. In theſe vertuous Souls ſo little accuſtom'd to love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> touch proves an incurable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they rely upon their haughtin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and their Greatneſs of Spirit, which often abuſes them, &amp; is ſometimes the inſtrument which betrays them to Love. The fair Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs full of her New Ideas, was drown'd in an Amorous amuſement from morning till night, when the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97088:29"/>King entred her Chamber with <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> by the hand, and pray'd her ſhe would for a little while take his little Miſtreſs into her care, and he would preſently return. The Lady's thoughts were at that time ſo diſtracted, ſhe heard not a word the King ſaid, and knew not what to anſwer him. He was not well pleaſed with it; and diſcovering a coldneſs and melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly in her countenance, he would have ask'd her the reaſon; but was haſtned into the Councel by buſineſs of extraordinary importance. <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> remain'd with the Marchioneſs, who taking an exacter view of her than formerly, thought her hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomer than ever; or that ſhe appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo at leaſt to her who already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be jealous. She ask'd her if ſhe had not a deſire to ſee <hi>Antonine:</hi> to which <hi>Dorothy</hi> having anſwered with a bluſh, 'twas long ſince ſhe ſaw him, and ſhe would be very glad to ſee him. Now, the Lady reply'd, ſhe
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97088:29"/>ſhould ſee him that evening, but the King muſt not know it: ſhe had hardly done ſpeaking, but <hi>Alice</hi> the Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper came in to let her know <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonine</hi> was at the door. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs bid <hi>Dorothy</hi> go into the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, to ſurprize him the more. She was willing to have the pleaſure of ſeeing him a moment in private, and make him ſenſible the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he had to her for the goodneſs ſhe expreſs'd towards him. And it was no ſmall favour for a Lady, who in point of honour had refus'd to intermeddle with the Amours of a King, to make her ſelf the Confident of a Shepherd and a Gardiner's Daughter. So much do we differ from our ſelves as occaſions moves us, ſo eaſy a matter is it to diſpenſe with ſcruples our paſſion are inclin'd to remove.</p>
            <p>
               <q>You are very punctual, <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſays ſhe, as he came in, and if I miſtake not, are come a little ſooner
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97088:30"/>than I appointed you.</q> 
               <q>Time ſeems long to thoſe in Love, Madam, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers he; and they are ſo fearful of coming too late to ſee their Miſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, they are always the firſt at the place of <hi>Rendez-vous.</hi>
               </q> 
               <q>I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd you, ſays the Lady, to let you ſee your Miſtreſs this evening, but do you know what a hazard I run, &amp; what trouble I ſhall create my ſelf, if this ſhould be known? Get you into that Cloſet for fear of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſeen; and if <hi>Dorothy</hi> comes to you, think very much your Friend.</q> 
               <hi>Antonine,</hi> not to loſe moments ſo precious, expreſt more by actions than words how ſenſible he was of the favours ſhe did him; and open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cloſet-door was extremly ſurpris'd at the ſight of the fair <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> dreſt all over with Jewels. The young Lover raviſh'd with joy, run preſently to him. But he received her with that coldneſs and ſadneſs, her heart was almoſt froz'n with fear:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97088:30"/>And ſhe forbore her careſſes to quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel him for expreſſing no more joy at the ſight of her after ſo tedious an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. He ſigh'd and made no other anſwer: <hi>Dorothy</hi> more troubled than before, ask'd him as one affrighted, what the matter was he us'd her ſo: The Shepherd was unwilling to be the firſt ſhould reproach her for what ſhe perhaps did not yet know; and and he had need enough to be better inform'd of, not to accuſe her without cauſe. He ask'd her firſt, whence ſhe had all thoſe Jewels he ſaw about her. <hi>Dorothy</hi> anſwer'd the King had given them her, and very ingenu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly told him all the Viſits and fine promiſes he had made her, and in a word all that paſt ſince her coming to the Marchioneſs. <hi>Antonine</hi> heard her out without ſaying a word, then turning another way in a mortal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, he lift up his eyes and hands to Heaven without further explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf. But <hi>Dorothy</hi> frightned
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97088:31"/>at the action, pray'd him ſo earneſtly, adding ſo many careſſes and tears to her prayers, that the Shepherd could no longer deny her the explication ſhe begg'd of him, who was ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently concerned without her intreaty to eaſe his heart a little by ſpeaking his mind. <q>
                  <hi>Dorothy,</hi> ſays he, the King is in love with you.</q> 
               <q>Well, I know it, anſwers ſhe, but if he loves me, he loves you too; and what harm in that?</q> 
               <q>What harm, replyes the dejected <hi>Antonine</hi> with a deep ſigh; None, but that I ſhall never ſee you more, but die with deſpair.</q> 
               <q>And why ſhould you die, ſays ſhe, alarmed at theſe words; and why ſee me no more, when the King who loves you, takes ſo much plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to ſee us together.</q> 
               <q>Yes, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes <hi>Antonine,</hi> do not you ſee that theſe three or four days I am not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd the liberty to enter this Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment? But 'tis over, I am un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done, and you are to expect no more
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97088:31"/>of me but my death.</q> Poor <hi>Dorothy</hi> oppreſt with grief at this Diſcourſe, gave free courſe to her tears, and embracing him tenderly, ask'd him what reaſon he had to wiſh for death, ſince ſhe loved him above her Life. <q>What am I the better for your Love, anſwers the Shepherd, when my Rival is poſſeſſed of you all day, and courts you, and is a King and can do what he pleaſes. Ah! how unfortunate am I!</q> 
               <q>Never fear the King, ſays the innocent <hi>Dorothy,</hi> for he hath promiſed me he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do any thing to diſpleaſe me.</q> 
               <hi>Antonine</hi> asked her, on what account he made her that promiſe; ſhe told him, it was upon occaſion of ſome little Favours he would have obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of her. A cruel explication for one ſo deeply in Love! He look'd upon her with a languiſhing Eye, and dying away for fear of hearing more than he deſired to know, he fell into a mournful and ſad ſilence; he was
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:97088:32"/>juſt expiring for grief, when on the ſudden he heard the King's voice in the Marchioneſſes Chamber. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing could have happened more effectual to fetch him again, than the approach of his Rival, jealouſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the paſſion that beſt quickens and moſt heightens the courage of a Lover.</p>
            <p>This Prince was under an Amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous impatience too ſtrong to permit him to ſtay long in the Councel: Affairs of State, and of Love never agree well, not that they are incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patible, or that a Great Genius is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>capable to bear at once the burthen of both. But this is very rare, and 'tis commonly ſeen he that acquits himſelf well of the one, is a little negligent of the other. This Prince having very able Miniſters, rely'd on them for the conduct of the State, that he might intirely apply himſelf to his affairs of Love. He was much addicted to that paſſion, and more
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:97088:32"/>ſenſible of the Pleaſure that attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it, than ambitious of the Glory of good Government: while they treated in his Cloſet of the moſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant affairs of his Crown, his mind was in the Marchioneſſes Chamber, where he had left his Heart with his Miſtriſs; but he was not a little ſurprized not to find her there at his return. He asked the Lady what was become of her, ſhe anſwered very coldly ſhe knew not. <q>I thought, Madam, anſwers the King, having left her to your Care a few minutes, I might have had a better account from you. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſir'd it of you, 'tis an innocent Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and knows not how to behave her ſelf; you might without wrong to your ſelf have inſtructed her a little, and told her ſhe was to wait my coming. But I perceive what the matter is—</q> 
               <q>I did not think, Sir, replies the Lady, that in leaving with me a Gardiners Daughter, you
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97088:33"/>deſir'd I ſhould be her Governeſs.</q> 
               <q>No indeed, ſays the King, but if you ſhould be her Governeſs, think you that to be employ'd ſo on my ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count could be a diſhonour to you.</q> 
               <q>Ah Sir! anſwers ſhe, with an affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſmile, I come of a Blood—</q> 
               <q>And you might have come (ſays the King, interrupting her angrily) of the beſt Blood of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and have eſteemed it an Honour, to ſerve a King as I am in any manner whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</q> With that he went out very little ſatisfied with the proceedings of the Marchioneſs, and ſent for Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> to make his complaints to him. <hi>Antonin</hi> and <hi>Dorothy</hi> were in very great perplexity having heard part of the diſcourſe, but the Shepherd was the more troubled of the two. The Lady bid <hi>Dorothy</hi> come into the Chamber, that if the King came back again, as ſhe feared he would, he might find her there. As for <hi>Antonin</hi> ſhe thought it not
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97088:33"/>convenient to let him come out for fear of being ſeen, and perhaps met by the King who was not far off: the mean time ſhe fell to inſtructing <hi>Dorothy</hi> what to ſay to the King, if he ſhould queſtion her for the little Eclipſe ſhe had been under: but ſhe was forc'd to cut off her Leſſon ſhort, for the Amorous Prince impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently deſirous to know if ſhe were returned, came preſently back and entred the Chamber with anger in his Face and much diſcompoſed, but at the ſight of <hi>Dorothy</hi> his Choler va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht, and he recovered his good humour.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs would have helped <hi>Dorothy</hi> to make her excuſe, and at the ſame time make her own peace with the King: But he could not hear her, but ſaid he was ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but entreated her to lend him her Cloſet, to paſs a few mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes with <hi>Dorothy</hi> there. This put the Lady into an extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:97088:34"/>perplexity, with all her coldneſs and indifferency ſhe could not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear bluſhing; ſhe knew not on what pretence to deny him; the key was in the door, and ſhe was ruin'd if the King found <hi>Antonin</hi> in the Cloſet. Poor <hi>Dorothy</hi> was no leſs diſordered, and though ſhe thought ſhe had no cauſe of being in fear for her Shepherd; yet ſhe could not rid her ſelf of the fear that follows things done in private. Had the King taken notice of her looks, they had all been undone. She had not then learnt the Art of concealing or commanding her paſſion: but by good fortune the King's Eyes were fixt on the Marchioneſs, who aſſiſted with the readineſs of Wit, which never fails an able Woman at need, entreated him to ſtay a moment till ſhe had put the Cloſet in a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition to receive them, every thing being out of order there. The King though in never ſo great haſte (belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97088:34"/>Ladies Cloſets are often full of ſeveral things that belong to their dreſſes, and they are very willing Men ſhould not ſee, and that this was the cauſe of her bluſhing) gave her leave to put it in order. She went into the Cloſet, and not well know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing where to hide the poor Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, ſhe put him under a bed of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, where he lay coop'd up in a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry narrow room. This done ſhe came out to make way for the King, who entred with <hi>Dorothy</hi> and made her ſit with him on the ſame Bed. Well <hi>Dorothy,</hi> ſays the King, you will never love me. The poor Girl who knew not what was become of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonine,</hi> ſurpriſed to miſs him in the Cloſet, looked all about, ſometimes this, ſometimes that way, without anſwering the King, who continued his diſcourſe; <q>I may tell you I ſigh and die for love of you, you can give me the hearing without pitty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſufferings for you.</q> 
               <hi>Dorothy</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:97088:35"/>heard not a word he ſaid, 'twas kindneſs thrown away; ſhe was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled for her Shepherd, and her ſenſe as well as mind was wholly taken up with thinking what was become of him. The King thinking 'twas the Ornaments, the guilding and rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Cloſet amuſed her, took her by the hand to make her look to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him; <q>Look upon me, and anſwer what I ask you, you little Baggage, will you never love me?</q> 
               <q>Yes, Sir, ſays ſhe, if you will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe me not to ſend away <hi>Antonine</hi> from <hi>Aranjuez.</hi>
               </q> 
               <q>And who told you, replies the King, I deſign to ſend him away—</q> 
               <q>No, Sir, ſays ſhe, I was not told ſo, but I know not why they will not let me ſee him, and I am afraid if I love you, you would not have me love him too:</q> 
               <q>And if I allow you to love him, anſwers the King, will you love me in good earneſt, or at leaſt as well as your Shepherd?</q> 
               <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:97088:35"/>made him no anſwer, not knowing how to reſolve that point without having <hi>Antonine</hi>'s advice in that caſe. The King fell a-laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and preſſing her farther, <q>Is it poſſible, ſays he, you ſhould think it ſo hard a matter to allow a King a ſhare with the Shepherd in your heart. Any other but you would have quickly ended the difference, and no other but my ſelf would be content with what I ask. You are not juſt, <hi>Dorothy,</hi> you demand of me what I ought not to grant you, and you make a buſineſs and a diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty to grant me what cannot but be for your Glory. You are afraid I ſhould ſend away <hi>Antonine,</hi> you complain you cannot ſee him; you would, if you love me, have me allow you to love him too: theſe are ſtrange conditions. And yet if I ask you whether you will love me as much as him, you will not anſwer me. What are you afraid of? I
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97088:36"/>would not have you conſider me as your King: among Lovers matters ſhould be equal at leaſt. Let's come to Articles, <hi>Dorothy,</hi> addes he ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and if I grant you yours, you muſt not refuſe to ſign mine. <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonine</hi> ſhall ſtay at <hi>Aranjuez,</hi> you ſhall ſee him and love him: This is for you. Now for my part, you muſt love me as well as him, and do me the ſame favours you do him, and if in time you find my care and my paſſion for you greater than the duties he pays you, without bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my Character or your duty to me into account, you will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to be intirely mine.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Prince, who was infinitely wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, would not make uſe of a Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gallantry to gain the affection of an innocent Countrey-Girl. He was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it, and made uſe only of plain native ſimplicity, ſo much the more delicate as it ſuited her capacity and wrought more effectually on her.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97088:36"/>The truth is, it ſhook her. So that the Monarch to take th'advantage of the agreement, began with kiſſes which ſhe could not refuſe him after the promiſes he had made her in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of <hi>Antonine:</hi> But the Shepherd ſcarce heard the ſmack of 'em, but all in a rage he pinch'd her by the Leg. This ſo frighted the poor Girl, that ſhe skrick'd, which aſtoniſht the King. He ask'd her what the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was; ſhe told him ſomething had bit her. By good luck for <hi>Antonine,</hi> there ſtood between the King and <hi>Dorothy</hi> a little Bitch of the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs's which came with them into the Cloſet; the King thought her guilty of the aſſault, and with great animoſity drove her out of the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet. But <hi>Dorothy,</hi> having had time to recover her ſelf a little from the fear ſhe had been in, judg'd her hurt came by the hand of a Man, rather than the teeth of the little Bitch: And re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting immediately on <hi>Antonine,</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97088:37"/>ſhe made no doubt but 'twas he, and that he lay hid under the Bed of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. The King having aſſur'd her ſhe need not fear being bit any more, would have been at his former ſport; but <hi>Dorothy</hi> would not agree to it, having underſtood by her Shepherd's action what ſhe had already done had not pleas'd him. The Prince preſs'd her, and ask'd why ſhe would be ſo cruel; but all was loſt labour, ſhe would not be brought to't for fear <hi>Antonine</hi> ſhould bite her the ſecond time. <q>You know our Agreement, <hi>Dorothy,</hi> ſays the King ſeeing her obſtinacy, I ſhall not be oblig'd to keep my promiſe with you if you refuſe what I demand of you. You muſt love me as well as you do <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonine,</hi> and expreſs the ſame com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance for me as for him, if you have a mind I ſhould allow him a a ſight of you, and not ſend him away from <hi>Aranjuez.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>Dorothy</hi> much troubled at theſe threats, knew
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97088:37"/>not what to anſwer. In the mean time ſhe granted nothing, but defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelf ſtill againſt the King's im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity, who thinking her light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs an effect of her humour, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to it her refuſing him ſo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinately what ſhe had granted at firſt without any difficulty, he eaſily flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd himſelf with hopes to obtain it another time, and without preſſing her further that evening, retir'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonine</hi> no ſooner ſaw him gone, but he crept out of his priſon, grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouſly tir'd with ſtaying ſo long there. <hi>Dorothy,</hi> to make him amends was liberal of her careſſes, but found him not ſo well pleas'd with her as to return them: His heart ſmarted ſtill with the ſound of the kiſſes the King had received of her, or at leaſt given her, which made <hi>Antonine</hi> requite her careſſes with reproaches. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs came in preſently, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved a little coldneſs between the two Lovers, which ſhe took no great
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97088:38"/>care to remove. And Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> coming in from the King, there was a neceſſity of parting.</p>
            <p>The fair Ladies went out of the Cloſet, where they lock'd in <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine,</hi> and the Marchioneſs went to <hi>Dorothy</hi>'s Chamber not far from her own; and having reſolv'd to ſtay there till the Marqueſs were abed, that ſhe might return to <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſhe made <hi>Dorothy</hi> relate all that paſt in the Cloſet.</p>
            <p>The Shepherd waited with impa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience enough to know what they would do with him. He could have been content to paſs that night in the Cloſet, in hopes of an opportunity to ſee <hi>Dorothy</hi> in the morning, having not yet told her half what he had to ſay to her, being juſt upon loſing her, not by any falſeneſs of hers, which he knew her incapable of, but through her innocence which madded him. He had a thouſand reflexions on what had paſt that evening, and the
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97088:38"/>conjectures he drew from them were very diſpleaſing: when on the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the Marchioneſs, opening the door ſoftly, entred ſmiling, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſhut it after her, <q>Well <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſays ſhe, with a low voice, you are my Priſoner.</q> 
               <q>'Tis true, Madam, anſwers he, I am ſo, and 'tis no ſmall honour for a Shepherd to have ſo fair a Lady (as you are) to his Goaler.</q> This Anſwer was a little too Gallant for a Lover, who ſhould have then been full of trouble and care, but he thought himſelf obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to ſome ſweetneſs and complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, towards a Lady who had been ſo much his Friend. <q>You are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd to ſtay here all Night, ſays the Lady.</q> 
               <q>I ſhall not complain of my ſentence, Madam, replies the Shepherd, and would to God it were all the ill I am like to ſuffer here.</q> The Lady preſently underſtood he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected on the King, but having a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to turn the diſcourſe another
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97088:39"/>way, ſhe made as if ſhe had not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended him; <q>there ſhall no ill befall you here, ſays ſhe, unleſs the Marqueſs chance to awake, and have the curioſity to come and ſee what I do thus late in this Cloſet. What would he ſay to find you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone with me here at this hour, and what would you do, if you had not time to hide your ſelf?</q> 
               <q>I know not in truth, Madam, ſays <hi>Antonine</hi> laughing, what I ſhould do, but what could he ſuſpect of a poor Shepherd?</q> 
               <q>Do you think becauſe you are but a Shepherd, anſwers ſhe, a Husband could reſt ſatisfied?</q> 
               <q>The Marqueſs, Madam, anſwers <hi>Antonine,</hi> is too well aſſured of your Virtue, to have any cauſe to fear the moſt preſumptuous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts.</q> 
               <q>The moſt ſevere Virtue, replies the Marchioneſs, may be lya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſuſpition (with Men leſs jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and leſs intereſted than the Marqueſs) when expos'd to a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97088:39"/>ſo handſome as you; and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally my Judge muſt be very indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and favourable, who knowing you have been alone with me at this hour lockt up in my Cloſet, and my Husband aſleep, will do me Juſtice, and think no more of the buſineſs. I muſt conſeſs I expoſe my ſelf a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, but I am uſually gain'd by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and find ſo much in you, I do not repent it.</q> 
               <hi>Antonine</hi> failed not to anſwer this exceſs of Goodneſs, in the moſt acknowledging, and moſt obliging expreſſions. He thought it a great happineſs to have gained the eſteem of ſuch a Lady. Yet could not this eaſe him of his ſufferings on <hi>Dorothie's</hi> account, though his pain was ſomewhat abated by the hopes he had this Lady would pity him, and eſpouſe his intereſt.</p>
            <p>The Night was far gone, and the Marchioneſs, who had more than one reaſon to undreſs and go to Bed, told <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſhe had for love of him
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97088:40"/>ſent back her Maids to their Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and that for once he muſt be her Chamber-Maid. <hi>Antonine</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertook the Office with a great deal of joy, and did it with ſo much neat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Gallantry, that of all ſhe had ſeen him do, the Lady moſt admir'd him for this. Being but a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, and a Shepherd that pleaſed her, ſhe was not very ſhye of him, nor obſerved the meaſures ſhe would have done with a Man of another Character. The time, place, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment ſhe gave him, permitted her not to keep the diſtance and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy uſual in thoſe caſes: And theſe ſecret affairs, though innocent, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire a Liberty into thoſe employed, they believe they are allowed to do any thing. The Marchioneſs laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and ſo did <hi>Antonine;</hi> ſhe permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her ſelf to be undreſt, juſt as he pleaſed, giving him occaſion to preſs very far, had he had the courage: But he was young, and knew not
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97088:40"/>how to uſe the complaiſance ſhe had for him. He had put her at laſt into a condition to want her Night-Gown; and if the Beauties he ſaw did not charm him, they at leaſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted him, and made him forget for ſome moments the troubles of that Evening. The Marchioneſs, though brown, had an excellent Complexion, and a Neck made to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire Treaſon into the admirers of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Beauties; Qualities the more eſteemed in <hi>Spain</hi> for their Rarity. Her Eyes were beautiful, and black, but ſo quick and piercing, you could ſcarce indure to look ſtedfaſtly on them. Her Mouth, her Noſe, her Teeth, and the reſt of her Face had not the leaſt blemiſh: Her Height, her Ayr, her Meen, were anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and it was not without reaſon the King had been in love with her, being unqueſtionably the handſomeſt Lady in the Kingdom. She looked from time to time upon <hi>Antonine,</hi> to
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97088:41"/>obſerve in his Countenance what ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect the ſight of ſome Beauties not ordinary wrought in him; and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him one time very buſie, ſhe put him back, whether out of anger or ſhame, I know not, and reſuming her ſerious Meen; <q>I cannot tell, ſays ſhe, what people would judge of me, if it ſhould be known at Court, I had allow'd you this liberty, I were ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly undone. Be ſure you let <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> know nothing of it, for ſhe is an innocent Girl, and will be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently jealous perhaps, and then tell it the King.</q> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Antonine</hi> anſwered her, Diſcretion was a virtue not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unknown to Shepherds:</q> 
               <q>I believe it, ſays ſhe, eſpecially to ſuch Shepherds as you, who are not born to be unhappy:</q> After this, ſhe bid him adieu, and having lock'd him up in the Cloſet, ſhe went to bed where ſhe did nothing all night but dream of him, and ſigh. She called to mind all he had ſaid, and
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97088:41"/>all ſhe had ſeen him do that Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and found not his Diſcourſe only, but the leaſt of his Actions were ſo unlike thoſe of the Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er he bore, ſhe could not poſſibly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him a Shepherd. Her heart at leaſt too proud to ſtoop ſo low, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to make her believe him a young Gentleman of Quality, who had diſguiſed himſelf for love of <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy.</hi> 
               <q>Happy Maid, ſays ſhe, ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, how few Women in the World but would be jealous of thy good Fortune, to have the affection of a Lover, the moſt tender, and moſt deſerving on Earth! Never was Love more gallant and paſſionate; never were ſentiments more eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and noble than his. Who can but be affected with them? what Virtue can withſtand ſo many Charms?</q> Theſe were her thoughts, of which ſhe was ſo full, the Idea of <hi>Antonine,</hi> intirely took up all her re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion, that ſhe minded not her ſighs
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:97088:42"/>which ſhe gave free vent to, with ſuch violence that they awak'd the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs; who asking her what ſhe ailed, ſhe was ſo ſurpriſed ſhe knew not what to ſay, but that ſhe was not very well. Don <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who was fond of her beyond meaſure, and knew her ſubject to vapours, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin'd that hindred her reſt, and would have gone to the Cloſet for a Viol of Eſſence, very good for that Diſtemper: but the Marchioneſs told him that was not the thing that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled her. But Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> would not be perſwaded from riſing to fetch the Eſſence, believing his Lady, to ſave him trouble, would not own her Diſtemper. This put the Marchioneſs to her ſhifts, ſo that to ſtay him, ſhe told him, 'twas only a Dream had frightned her, and kept her from ſleeping, and that nothing elſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled her. The Marqueſs having ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted her there was no notice to be taken of Dreams, being an effect
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97088:42"/>only of a wandring imagination, of which no account is to be made, asked her, what ſhe dream't. She ſeem'd very loth to tell him; but being very much preſſed by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, who ſaid he would eaſe her of the conceit of it; to ſatisfie him, ſhe had preſently this dream. (For before ſhe had dream't of nothing but <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine:)</hi> 
               <q>Alas! Sir, ſays ſhe, with a deep ſigh, I thought I was with Child, and brought to Bed of an Infant ſo big and ſo monſtrous, I died for very grief. With that I awak'd, much troubled to know what ill this dream ſignify'd; and having pray'd Heaven to be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to me, I made a Vow not to lie with you for nine days.</q> Don <hi>Auſtin,</hi> to comfort her, made the moſt favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able interpretation he could imagin of the dream, running over all he knew in Story, Sacred and Profane, of the dreams of <hi>Daniel,</hi> King <hi>Ahaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erus,</hi> and many others he told her of,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97088:43"/>to let her ſee 'twas good to dream of being delivered of an extraordinary Child: But like a good Man he was willing ſhe ſhould perform her Vow, and to have it over the ſooner, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſhe ſhould begin that very day.</p>
            <p>Any Man but the Marqueſs would have nullify'd the Vow as againſt the laws of Matrimony, or at leaſt, ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected it feign'd to colour ſome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous treaſon; but he who was firmly perſwaded of the Vertue and Piety of his Wife as an Article of Faith, would have been very ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous to entertain the leaſt doubt of the ſincerity of her intentions. 'Twas time for him to get up if he meant to wait upon the King at his riſing: And as he was dreſſing, he diſcourſed his Wife all the while about the vanity of dreams, that ſhe might be unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, and make no more ſuch Vows. He gave not over talking till he went out of the Chamber, and had ſo tired his Lady with the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97088:43"/>ſhe wiſht from her heart ſhe had never ſpoken to him of a dream. And ſhe was not a little glad to be rid of him. He was no ſooner gone, but ſhe took her Night-gown, and ſlips ſoftly into the Cloſet where ſhe found <hi>Antonine</hi> aſleep on the Bed of Repoſe. She would not awake him, that ſhe might view him at more lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. And ſitting on a ſtool by him, there was not a feature in his Face but ſhe examined narrowly, and Love at the ſame time imprinted it in her heart. She fancied a thouſand things of his Perſon, imagining ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times this, ſometimes that; and out of love or curioſity did ſo long to be ſatisfied, that nothing but the fear of awaking him could have kept her back. At laſt, between ſtrugling with, and yielding to motions more prevalent than all her conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Honour and Decency, ſhe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventured (not without bluſhing) to kiſs him. The Happy Shepherd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wak'd
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97088:44"/>at it, was ſurpriz'd at the ſight of her, much more at the favour ſhe had done him. <q>You load me with favours, Madam, ſayes he half aſleep.</q> 
               <q>If you knew, anſwers ſhe, lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him in a very languiſhing manner, all the kindneſs I have for you! but do not abuſe it: For you ſee, adds ſhe, opening her Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gown, to let him ſee ſhe had no more on, with what complaiſance and familiarity I uſe you. You ſee me juſt as I came out of Bed, and if you are not diſcreet, 'tis the laſt time you ſhall ſee me ſo.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The troubled <hi>Antonine</hi> made a ſorry return for ſo Charming Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; he put on a very ſerious face, and full of reſpect, like a right Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-Shepherd. The Marchioneſs was that day handſomer than ever he had ſeen her. <hi>Antonine</hi> wanted neither Eyes not Wit, but he was young and and play'd the Innocent. So much Favour on the ſudden having perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97088:44"/>confounded him. But by little and little, he began to be fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar, and the Marchioneſs who was almoſt out of conceit with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to have ſome hopes of him: but the Houſe-keeper interrupted very unſeaſonably, and hindred the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence of the pleaſant Converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by coming to tell her Lady, that <hi>Dorothy</hi> in great haſte and earneſtneſs deſired to ſee her. The Marchioneſs gave her ſmall thanks for her pains, letting her ſee by her looks how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing her meſſage was. But there was no remedy; ſhe muſt give place to her Rival: And turning towards <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſhe ask'd him, if he would be glad to ſee <hi>Dorothy: Antonine</hi> had the civility not to appear very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of it, though he longed for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more. But the Marchioneſs who needed no inſtruction, ſeeing his Civility, and ſatisfy'd with his indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, (though but affected) to make him ſenſible what complaiſance ſhe
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97088:45"/>had for him, bid the Houſe-keeper let <hi>Dorothy</hi> in. <hi>Antonine</hi> pray'd her to ſtay and hear their diſcourſe: The Marchioneſs look'd upon him, and with a malicious ſmile, <q>I know, ſays ſhe, you deſire nothing leſs than what you ask; and if I had a mind to puniſh you, I would ſtay; but be not afraid on't, 'tis not my deſign. And I am more concern'd for your Amours than to take pleaſure in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Eye-witneſs of your careſſes to another.</q> With that ſhe went out of the Cloſet, and got her to Bed again. The Houſe-keeper let in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> into the Marchioneſs's Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, where having paid her devoirs and deſir'd leave to go into her Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, ſhe went to her <hi>Antonine.</hi> The Shepherd receiv'd her with a more pleaſing air than the night afore: the anger of Lovers is very ſhort-lived; but the truth is, the Favours of the Marchioneſs had not a little contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to put him in good humour. In
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97088:45"/>the mean time the Marchioneſs had a ſad part to act, and had dearly paid with ſighs and vexation for the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect pleaſure of that morning, had not the King, who was in ſearch of <hi>Dorothy,</hi> ſent in the <hi>Duenna</hi> to know if ſhe were with the Marchioneſs. She could not have wiſh'd a better pretence for parting the two Lovers. And not to loſe the advantage of it, would have preſently ſent <hi>Dorothy</hi> back into her own Chamber to keep the King there; but he came in, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her (upon the news he had from Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſhe had had an ill night on't) he thought nothing but Love could have broken ones ſleep, but ſince it happen'd the moſt inſenſible Perſons could not reſt, it was ſome comfort to him for the many ill nights that Paſſion had cauſed him. The Marchioneſs, who wanted neither Gallantry nor Wit, return'd him an anſwer ſuitable to the ſubject. But the King thinking ſhe needed reſt, told
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97088:46"/>her, he would not add a new diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance to that ſhe had been afflicted with; and taking <hi>Dorothy</hi> by the hand, led her into her Chamber. The Marchioneſs happily deliver'd at once of two Perſons who troubled her more than all the World beſides, run ſtraight into the Cloſet to bring her dear Shepherd the news; but he was no leſs griev'd at it, than ſhe was joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. It was not in his power quite to conceal from her the rage he was in for jealouſie of the King. He ſpoke with ſome heat of the Amorous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution that Prince afflicted a young Maid with; inſomuch that he let fall a word, That it was the part of a Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant rather than a Juſt Monarch, to force one to love him. The Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs did but laugh and railly at him to be ſo paſſionate. But taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of thoſe laſt words, and the action he expreſt them with, ſhe diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a boldneſs and hardineſs in his countenance, which did but too clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97088:46"/>evidence the Greatneſs of his Soul. 'Twas not the firſt time ſhe had ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected him to be of quite another Quality, than what he pretended to, her paſſion and opinion of Honour, having perſwaded her he was not of ordinary Birth. But in the tranſport he was in on that occaſion, there flaſh'd out ſuch a fire out of his Eyes, which with the liberty he took in ſpeaking of the King, appear'd ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, that ſhe begun thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forwards to uſe him as ſhe believ'd he deſerved. And after ſhe had for ſome moments fixt her Eyes on him, <q>Sir, ſays ſhe, for I cannot call you <hi>Antonine</hi> any longer; I am your Friend, and you cannot doubt it: If the freedom I uſe with you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve any confidence from you, deny me not a requeſt I am making to you. Let me know the truth of a thing you can no longer conceal from me. This Shepherd's Habit you are in, ſuit better with your
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:97088:47"/>love to <hi>Dorothy</hi> than your Birth: you have not ſufficiently diſguiſed your ſelf from me, or rather I have too long, and too ſtudiouſly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved you, not to ſee your actions, and your words, the Ayr and Grace of your Perſon, belye the habir you have taken: Had you confin'd your ſelf to playing on the Flute, and keeping Sheep, you might have paſt for a Shepherd; but when you meddle with othes things you are diſcovered with half an eye. Hide your ſelf no longer from me, who truſt my ſelf with you. I confeſs, I am much concerned in it, and this makes me ſo curious: If you fear only my revealing the ſecret, aſſure your ſelf, I will keep it as religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly as you could deſire from the beſt Friend you have in the World, for I am certainly ſhe.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Antonine,</hi> who was a little diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at the Ladies firſt words, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving by this time recover'd himſelf,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97088:47"/>fell a-laughing, and told her it was her exceſs of goodneſs made her uſe him better than he deſerved, that he was no more than the Son of a poor Shepherd near <hi>Toledo.</hi> And that if there were any thing in him extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary beyond thoſe of his condition, he was beholding for it to Nature, not Birth. All this could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade the Lady from the opinion ſhe had of his Quality; but ſhe told him that ſhe would, if he deſir'd it, ſtill call him <hi>Antonine,</hi> and uſe him in publick like a Shepherd; but as for her particular, ſhe very well knew the difference ſhe was to make; And that he might have already conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the freedom ſhe had uſed with him, ſhe had not been long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd. <hi>Antonine</hi> made but a weak defence, telling her at laſt, <q>ſhe might reſt aſſured, if there were any thing in his Life that deſerv'd confidence, ſhe ſhould be the firſt that he would impart it to.</q> The Marchioneſs
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97088:48"/>underſtanding what it meant, preſſed him no further: And Dinner-time being come, ſhe ſent for it into her Chamber, as being indiſpoſed, that ſhe might have the pleaſure of ſeeing <hi>Antonine</hi> dine with her. The <hi>Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enna</hi> told them, the King did as much with <hi>Dorothy,</hi> having dined in his Chamber, to have her Company the whole day.</p>
            <p>The Marchioneſs was raviſhed at the News, and <hi>Antonine</hi> began to be leſs troubled at it. Not but that his paſſion for <hi>Dorothy</hi> was ſtill very great, but that the thoughts he then had of the King, had filled him with rage and vexation, that he was glad of the opportunity he had to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged of <hi>Dorothy,</hi> or at leaſt to be even with her. He ſaw her Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence could not long hold out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the love of that Prince; and he was ſo mad at her for it, he began to form a deſign to abandon her quite. But how unjuſt are Lovers in theſe
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97088:48"/>caſes? What could a poor innocent Girl do, that had in a manner not ſeen the World above three days, who knew nothing of Love, but what he had taught her, nor could diſtinguiſh what did, from what did not belong to a Lover; but believed, that, except one thing, all was free for the King, as for <hi>Antonine;</hi> what could ſhe do? Beſides, ſhe was to deal with a King, who was a great Maſter of the Art of Love, and infinitely witty: which with the advantages of Majeſty might have prevailed with a Maid more experienced, and more difficult, than <hi>Dorothy</hi> to be gain'd.</p>
            <p>In that unquiet condition the Shepherd's Heart had reaſon to be in, 'twas no ſmall comfort to have the kindneſs of a fair Lady, as the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, to qualifie his misfortunes: ſhe was a charming Woman, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently skilled in the Art of pleaſing, and forgot nothing that might tempt
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:97088:49"/>him to a deſertion; ſighs, kindneſſes, languiſhing looks, tenderneſs, obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging actions, all the moſt pleaſant poiſons of Love were made uſe of, and to very good purpoſe. Here was cauſe enough of fear for <hi>Dorothy,</hi> had not her good fortune delivered her from the King; and 'tis uncertain what would become of her, had ſhe ſtaid a moment longer out of the Marchioneſſes Chamber. Such pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er hath a fair Lady in Love over Hearts, however engaged or indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent: That Women how deeply ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever in Love with another, can reſiſt the Engines and Artifices Love in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires her to make uſe of.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Duenna</hi> had acquainted them with <hi>Dorothie's</hi> coming, that they had time enough to put themſelves in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, though any other but <hi>Dor.</hi> might have however found cauſe enough of ſuſpition in the very eyes of the Marchioneſs: But <hi>Dorothy</hi> was inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, and had too good an opinion of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97088:49"/>her Shepherd, to whom without his asking her, ſhe preſently gave account of all that paſt in the extraordinary viſit His Majeſty had made her. She was ſo ingenuous not to conceal from him the favours ſhe was forced to grant him, having terribly threatned to ruine him, and ſend him away where ſhe ſhould never ſee him, if ſhe were not as complaiſant to him as to <hi>Antonine.</hi> The Shepherd from time to time ſhrug'd his Shoulders as ſhe talked, and when ſhe had done, asked if this were her faithfulneſs to him. <hi>Dorothy</hi> who thought ſhe had done nothing againſt the duty of one in Love, in complying a little to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the ſtrange menaces the King u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, would have juſtified her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct with reaſons, which quite drove poor <hi>Antonine</hi> to deſpair. <q>That is, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupts he, had the King put it to your choice to have me baniſht your ſight, or comply with his paſſion; you would have preferred the ſhame
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97088:50"/>of yielding your ſelf up to him, to the diſpleaſure of my abſence.</q> 
               <q>What would you have had me have done, replies ſhe, with ſome tears to ſee him ſpeak as he did.</q> The Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs was preſent at this Comedy, and had all the divertiſement of it. <hi>Antonine</hi> and <hi>Dorothy</hi> continued long in diſpute, without her taking either party. But the King coming ſo ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly, that the <hi>Duenn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> had ſcarcely time to tell her Lady, he was like to have ſurpriſed them all three. He went into the Cloſet, and having complemented the Marchioneſs, ſat him down on the bed there, and ſhe went out, leaving him and <hi>Dorothy</hi> together, who reſolved to repair her fault: for let the King beg, threaten, fret himſelf never ſo much; ſay, do what he pleaſe, ſhe would not ſo much as let him kiſs her hand, which put him almoſt beſide himſelf; and made <hi>Antonine</hi> glad at heart. Well done <hi>Dorothy,</hi> thinks he, this is brave,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97088:50"/>thou revengeſt me to purpoſe for the torment he hath put me to.</p>
            <p>The King finding <hi>Dorothies</hi> hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour ſo ſtrangely altered, ſince he parted with her, being not above an hour or two; imputed it to ſome ridiculous counſels the Marchioneſs, with whom he found her, might have given her in ſome unſeaſonable Principles and Precepts of Virtue. He turned all his anger that way, and as he went out of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber he made it ſufficiently appear to the Lady, he was not well ſatisfied with the good offices ſhe had done him: He paſt by her without ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a word, quite contrary to the obliging carriage he always uſed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards her. The Marchioneſs was extremely ſurpriſed at it, and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her fear to that ſhe was moſt careful of, ſhe fancied the King had diſcovered <hi>Antonine</hi> in the Cloſet, which made him look ſo angry:
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97088:51"/>ſhe ran ſtrait to <hi>Dorothy</hi> to know the News, and perceived by the Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, her rigours had put him out of humour. This was preſently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Don <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who came in ſhortly after to tell her, the King had complained bitterly of her, for the ill inſtructions ſhe had given <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy:</hi> And that if ſhe took not heed, ſhe would ruine him. Time was, when a complaint of this Nature would have been very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive, but it was in the days of Yore; ſhe had now changed her humour, and was become more tractable. She eaſily defended her ſelf againſt the King's Charge, and expreſt that zeal for the concerns of his paſſion, that ſhe told Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> he might aſſure his Majeſty, it ſhould be no fault of hers, if he were not ſucceſsful. There was reaſon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for it, ſhe did her own buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by it: and had the King known how far ſhe was engag'd on his part,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97088:51"/>and concerned to promote his inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſts, he would never have ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her of the injury he charged her with. Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> went directly to bring the King the News, and the Marchioneſs ſtept immediately in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Cloſet, to laugh with <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine,</hi> who could not heartily thank her for making a party againſt him, yet, knowing the reaſon of it, he could not be much diſpleaſed.</p>
            <p>The Marqueſs came the ſecond time to tell his Wife, the King was well ſatisfied with the expreſſions of her good will; and pray'd her if ſhe would not do him ſervice, which he would not adventure to deſire of her, yet that ſhe would not make a Confederate againſt him. She not only promiſed this, but added, that upon all occaſions the King ſhould find her for him, and that ſhe would never ſpeak to <hi>Dorothy</hi> but for his advantage. Perſons of her Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter, where they allow themſelves
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:97088:52"/>liberty, become more indulgent to others in like caſes. Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> was the firſt that gave her thanks, being ſo well pleaſed with her that Evening, that had it not been for her Vow, he would have done ſomewhat extraordinary that night, to let her know how much ſhe had obliged him, in eſpouſing the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of a Monarch, whom next her, he loved the beſt of any living, this was excellent divertiſement for the Marchioneſs: At laſt the viſit and converſation of the too grateful Marqueſs, was ſo long, ſhe began to be a weary of him, and very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be rid of him. His ſtay was no leſs troubleſome to <hi>Dorothy,</hi> who having left the Cloſet when the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs came forth, wiſht him gone preſently that ſhe might return. But the Marqueſs having been ſo taken up all day with State-affairs, that he had not time to pay his Lady the duties of a kind Husband, thought
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97088:52"/>himſelf that day more than ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to keep her company in the Evening, after the complaiſance ſhe had expreſt in what concerned the King. The Marchioneſs and <hi>Dor.</hi> roſe from their Seats, they walk'd about, they held their peace, but all to no purpoſe, he ſtir'd not till it was time for his Wife to go to bed, and he would not leave her till he ſaw her a-Bed, and paſt ſome kind comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to comfort her againſt the ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of her Vow, praying her par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly never to make the like a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain. <hi>Dorothy</hi> was forced to retire and go to Bed, though much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, and angry, ſhe could not ſee <hi>Antonine.</hi> But he was reſerved for the Marchioneſs, who had no ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er lodg'd her Husband ſafe, and commanded the <hi>Duenna</hi> to make all the doors faſt, but ſhe got up, and told her dear <hi>Antonine,</hi> hemight come out of the Cloſet, the coaſt was all clear, and they had the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:97088:53"/>whole Chamber for themſelves. <q>Yes, Madam, anſwers the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, but if the Marqueſs ſhould come on the ſudden, and I not have time to hide my ſelf, what would he think?</q> 
               <q>Alas! nothing, ſays ſhe, what ſhould he fear from a Shepherd, ſo diſcreet and ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt?</q> 
               <q>I know not, replies <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine,</hi> laughing; but what you told me yeſterday, (it would be very hard not to ſuſpect ſomething, if any found me, (as very a Shepherd as I am) lock'd up with you at this time of night) made ſuch impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon me, that I begin in good earneſt to be afraid.</q> 
               <q>Fear nothing, ſays ſhe, laughing alſo, I am a good virtuous Lady, and Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> believes me ſo, and the pity I have to ſee you ſo ill lodg'd in the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, makes me willing to give you half of my Bed if you dare lie there, I mean upon the Bed, for it would not be handſome for a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:97088:53"/>as you are, or a Lady as I am, it ſhould be any otherwiſe. And to let you know what a Favour I do you, I can tell you 'tis more than the King in the height of his paſſion could ever obtain from me.</q> 
               <q>It was doubtleſs, Madam, ſayes <hi>Antonine,</hi> becauſe you were afraid he would not uſe the Favour di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcreetly enough, and are well aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured of the reſpect I bear you.</q> 
               <q>'Tis rather, ſays ſhe, playing with him, that I loved not the King, that he had not the Art to pleaſe me, and that <hi>Antonine—</hi>
               </q> She ſtopt there. <q>
                  <hi>Antonine,</hi> Madam, anſwers he, is happier than all the Kings up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth, in that he hath gained the Favour of ſo fair a Lady as the Marchioneſs <hi>De las Torillas:</hi> He hath nothing more to wiſh for but a Heart to offer and dedicate whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to her. But alas! I have it not.</q> 
               <q>Ah! Cruel, ſays ſhe, interrupting him, why do you mind me of it?
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:97088:54"/>why ſpeak you of a thing I do all I can to forget? Permit me to fancy, adds ſhe, with tender and languiſhing looks, that you neither love nor will love any but me: And if it be not altogether true, yet allow me to ſay ſo, and deceive my ſelf, which in this I am very willing to do.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I know not what this happy Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd thought then, but I believe him in ſome perplexity. He was forc'd in honour to anſwer civilly ſo much kindneſs and tenderneſs! the Lady was the moſt obliging, as well as the moſt Beautiful of the Court; and had ſuch a winning way with her, a Man muſt be very ill-natur'd to deny any thing ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired: It is eaſie to gueſs how two Perſons ſo well agreed, ſpent the reſt of the Night. You may preſume <hi>Antonine</hi> ſtrain'd a point, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted a little treaſon againſt his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to <hi>Dorothy.</hi> And if the Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:97088:54"/>of any Lover be proof againſt ſuch a temptation, it deſerves to be Chronicled.</p>
            <p>The King had not ſo good a night as <hi>Antonine,</hi> fretting and vexation fell to his Majeſties let, and having not ſlept till towards morning, he lay a-bed longer than ordinary. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> would fain have made uſe of that time to ſee <hi>Antonine,</hi> but the <hi>Duenna</hi> had her Leſſon; and told her, That her Lady had been ill all night, and muſt not be diſturbed. <hi>Dorothy</hi> reply'd, ſhe would make no noiſe, and only go into the Cloſet. She might have as well held her peace. The <hi>Duenna</hi> found reaſons enough to deny her, till the King came to talk with her; and ſoon af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Marqueſs, who ſent in the <hi>Duenna</hi> to ſee if his Wife were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſleep; ſhe brought him word, her Lady was newly awake; and he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the Chamber, and told her, ſhe muſt needs riſe, and go to <hi>Belviſo,</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:97088:55"/>where the King dined that day: The Marchioneſs excus'd her ſelf, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending ſhe was indiſpos'd. But the Good Man her worthy Spouſe told her, if ſhe would but endeavour to go ſo far, being but a walk, where the Air and Divertiſement would certainly recover her, ſhe would very much oblige the King, who would not go without her, and ſcarce believe ſhe was ill, having that morning a complexion more freſh and more beautiful than ever. The Marchioneſs could not forbear laughing to ſee how Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jol'd her. And finding what-ever ſhe did ſhe was not to expect being at liberty that after-noon, ſhe choſe rather to pleaſe the King, and avoid the occaſion of giving perhaps ſome umbrage, by pretending an indiſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which by her Husband's re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port ſhe could not ſufficiently feign. She took her time to give <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> notice of this Walk, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:97088:55"/>him what a trouble it was to her to leave him, putting it to his choice to ſtay there or go along. <hi>Antonine</hi> told her, he muſt needs get forth, and appear at his Lodging, where <hi>Dorot.</hi> Parents were doubtleſs much concern'd what was become of him, having not layn there theſe two nights. The Marchioneſs wiſht him to come again at night, and ſhe would give the <hi>Duenna</hi> orders, ſo that he ſhould need only to apply himſelf to her for entrance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Belviſo</hi> is a Houſe of Pleaſure within two miles of <hi>Aranjuez,</hi> the moſt agreeable and charming in all <hi>Spain.</hi> 'Tis a little enchanted Caſtle in the middle of a Lake, at the point of a Valley, than which nothing can be more delightful to the Eye. The Caſtle both without and within is equally rich, painted, and guilded all over, which glitters admirably in the Sun. 'Tis all of wood, and ſo curiouſly carved, that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:97088:56"/>more rare and more curious for Invention or Work. All the Chambers may be lower'd or rais'd at pleaſure, by Screws and Machines. And though but four, and a Hall in the middle, they have a way to make them appear twelve ſeveral Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, different not only in Furniture and Ornament, but in Figure.</p>
            <p>The King being arriv'd at the ſide of the Lake, embarqued in a Canot with the Marqueſs, his Lady, <hi>Dorothy,</hi> for whom the Entertainment was deſigned, with two or three other Ladies, and ſome principal Lords of the Court to go to the Caſtle. In the mean time they were troubled <hi>Antonine</hi> appeared not. 'Tis not the King was ſo concern'd, but <hi>Dorothy</hi> and the Marchioneſs, who look'd a good while round about them to ſee if he were come. <hi>Dorothy</hi> had never been in that Caſtle, and the King would in Perſon give her the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of ſeeing it; and for love of her,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:97088:56"/>ſet all the Machines of thoſe moving Chambers a-work. He was ſcarce got to the third, but <hi>Dorothy</hi> diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd, not by the force of any Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chine, but becauſe ſhe ſtay'd in the ſecond Room; the King not willing ſome Lords about him ſhould take notice of the concern he was in for her, went forwards, hoping in ſo ſmall a place he could not long want her. And indeed he found her in the ſecond Room ſpeaking to one of the Pages. He ſurpriz'd them, and asked <hi>Dorothy</hi> laughing, if ſhe had any office of Gallantry to imploy that Page in, that ſhe was in ſo private diſcourſe with. She bluſh'd a little, &amp; fell a-laughing too, at the King's not knowing the Page. This made the King fix his Eye upon him; and with no ſmall ſurprize diſcover him to be <hi>Antonine.</hi> 
               <q>And how long is it, ſays he to him, that you are turn'd from a Shepherd into a Page?</q> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> anſwer'd, But from that very
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:97088:57"/>morning,</q> having a deſire to ſee the Caſtle; and finding there was ſuch order given, that there was no get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in but in his Livery, he had bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row'd a Page's Coat for the purpoſe. The King ſaid no more to him; but ſcarce took any pleaſure the reſt of the time he ſpent there, having al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt always this Shepherd in his Eye, ſpeaking conſtantly to <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy:</hi> which put the King in no ſmall trouble and perplexity with his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing himſelf as much as poſſible to hide the concern he was in. His paſſion for <hi>Dorothy</hi> had not yet been much taken notice of, and he was willing to obſerve ſome meaſures in publique; ſo that he found it very difficult to be in private with her there. <hi>Antonine</hi> making uſe of the liberty the King allow'd him, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him where-ever he went, as well as the Lords and Ladies of his Train, and ſeem'd to affect keeping cloſe to <hi>Dorothy</hi> more than ever. The King
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:97088:57"/>might have got rid of him by ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to Land; but 'twould have been too apparent, and what pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ſoever he had taken, they would have gueſſed at the true cauſe. So that the very maxims of Decency forced the King to permit a Shepherd, under his very noſe, to croſs his deſires, to torment him, and raviſh from him undiſturb'd what he beſt loved in the World, without the Kings daring to complain of it, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs the leaſt reſentment: Only he ſpoke of it to the Marqueſs his ſole Confident, who had pray'd him to let him know the cauſe of the diſorder that appear'd in his countenance. This Faithful Miniſter of Love as well as State, having learnt what it was, reſolved at any rate to eaſe him of the ſight of the Shepherd, at leaſt for ſome time. He thought of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ways to do it, but knowing that Women are generally better than Men at ſuch matters, he went
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:97088:58"/>to his Wife; and taking her into another Room, ask'd her, if ſhe could not device ſome means to take that Shepherd aſide, who troubled the Entertainment, and get him kept out of the King's preſence, without ſending him to Land, which the King for ſome reaſons was unwilling to do. The Marchioneſs very offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly propoſed two or three ways, which indeed were neither proper nor approved by the Marqueſs. At laſt ſhe told him, That to diſabuſe the King, and wipe out the ill-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions he had taken of her conduct as to <hi>Dorothy,</hi> ſhe would ſerve him on this occaſion, and take <hi>Antonine</hi> into another Room, under pretence of making him play on the Flute, and would keep him there as long as he pleaſed; but ſhe feared 'twould be to his coſt, and that the World was malicious enough to talk of ſuch a thing. Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laughing heartily at the apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:97088:58"/>of his Vertuous Wife, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing her with extreme kindneſs, told her, Her Reputation was ſo friendly eſtabliſhed, it would never be ſuſpected, though there were no more Vertue nor Honour in the World. That ſhe might take his word for't, who was moſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And that it could not be at leaſt a Shepherd could do him any injury. Having ſaid this, he pray'd her to do as ſhe propoſed; adding ſhe would do the King a ſingular pleaſure, being no longer able to endure the ſight of the Shepherd. The Marchioneſs failed not to do it; and with an Addreſs her affection, more than any deſign to pleaſe the King or oblige her Husband, inſpir'd with, ſhe drew <hi>Antonine</hi> aſide from <hi>Dorothy,</hi> and took him to another Chamber, where ſhe ſtay'd with him till they went back for <hi>Aranjuez.</hi> The King was never the better for it: <hi>Dorothy</hi> did but fret and vex when
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:97088:59"/>ſhe loſt ſight of <hi>Antonine,</hi> and her Eyes diſcovered the trouble ſhe was in, not to know what was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of him.</p>
            <p>The Sun was ſet when they came to <hi>Aranjuez.</hi> And the King having a deſire to take a turn or two in the Garden, the whole Court follow'd him, except the Marchioneſs, who had deſigns in her Head; and hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accompanied her Husband a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>while, told him ſhe was not very well and muſt withdraw. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs more civil and kind than ſhe wiſht, brought her to her Chamber, and bore her company till ſhe was quite tyr'd with him. She undreſt her ſelf, ſhe went to bed, ſhe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain'd her Head ach'd, and that ſhe muſt go to reſt; and not knowing what to ſay or do more, ſhe order'd the Windows ſhould be ſhut, that the light might not trouble her in the morning; but Don <hi>Auſtin's</hi> Love was the ſame in the dark as in the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:97088:59"/>light. But ſhe muſt ſend him away at laſt, telling him the trouble ſhe was in he ſhould be there in the dark, and ſhe not able to ſpeak to him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed her malady and kept her from ſleeping. The good Marqueſs charm'd with the kindneſs of his dear Spouſe, took his leave of her, praying her ſhe would ſend for him, if ſhe grew worſe in the night. The Marqueſs was ſcarce gone, but the <hi>Duenna</hi> came in to let her Lady know <hi>Antonine</hi> was in her Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; the Marchioneſs bid her let him into hers, and immediately the <hi>Duenna</hi> led in a Shepherd who was not a little ſurpriz'd at the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Lodging: the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs imagining his ſurprize at the Novelty, fell a-laughing as ſoon as ſhe heard him come near the Bed; and reaching out her hand to him, <q>Fear nothing, ſays ſhe, this is all done for you, and you know you are not in an Enemies Country;</q> ſhe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:97088:60"/>made him ſit on her Bed, and going on with her diſcourſe told him the Darkneſs was a Friend to fearful <q>Lovers as you are. But you are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mute methinks <hi>Antonine,</hi> why do not you anſwer me?</q> She had ſcarce ſaid this, but in comes the <hi>Duenna</hi> almoſt out of breath, to tell her the Marqueſs was coming with a Flambo, and was juſt at the Chamber-door. <q>Go hide you in the Cloſet,ſays the Marchioneſs to her Shepherd:</q> but finding he ſtirr'd not, ſhe was aſtoniſh'd, and puſhing him with her hand, <q>do not you hear what they ſay, Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> is juſt here, go hide your ſelf, unleſs you will ruine both me and your ſelf.</q> With that the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs entred, who told his Wife he was very ſorry he muſt diſturb her, but he had loſt a Paper of great importance to the King, and muſt needs have left it on her Bed. The affrighted Marchioneſs being then ſo
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:97088:60"/>angry with <hi>Antonine</hi> ſhe wiſh'd him hang'd, told him, <q>you come the moſt ſeaſonably in the World to chaſtiſe a Fool; an Inſolent Fellow came into my Chamber the very moment you were gone, and has put me into a moſt terrible fright, ſitting upon my Bed, and I cannot remove him.</q> The Marqueſs aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſht at the inſolence, ran towards the Beds Feet; and in the Wrath he was in againſt ſuch an impudent Raſcal, not willing to be at the pains of examining who he was, he look'd only for a ſtick, to baſte him into better manners, and teach him the reſpect due to his Wives Bed; when he heard the Kings Voice who was diſguis'd like a Shepherd, and fell a laughing to ſee himſelf upon the point of being bang'd, and bid the Marqueſs open his Eyes and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate his fury: What a deadly blow was this to the Marqueſs! he turn'd pale and diſmay'd, he
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:97088:61"/>could not ſpeak a Word: at laſt having recovered his Spirits, <q>Ah, Sir, is it thus, a King as you are keep his Word? Have you done me ſo many Favours, only to rob me of my Honour? Ah Heavens! (cries he quite diſtracted,) have I lived thus long to ſee my ſelf loaded with Infamy by a Prince for whom I would have loſt my Blood!</q> Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſaid this he withdrew. The King would have ſtaid him, that he might clear himſelf before the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs of the unjuſt ſuſpicion he had of him, but he had not the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience to hear him. The King fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low'd him, that he might diſengage himſelf from a Lady, who had more reaſon than the Marqueſs to complain of him; though in truth he was not in fault towards the one or the other, as will appear by the truth of the adventure.</p>
            <p>For the King ſtaid not long in the Garden, having not been well ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfi'd
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:97088:61"/>with <hi>Dorothy</hi> all that day, and being full of ſuſpicion and jealouſie of her, he let her go where ſhe pleas'd, not doubting but a rendezvouz had been agreed on at the enterview be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween her and <hi>Antonine</hi> at <hi>Bellviſo;</hi> To ſee whether his ſuſpicions were well-grounded, he reſolved to put a trick on her, and going to his Chamber took the Shepherds Habit he formerly made uſe of, and put it on. His deſign was to go pray the Marchioneſs to help him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive <hi>Dorothy,</hi> and ſend her to him under the name of <hi>Antonine.</hi> He came for that purpoſe into her Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and within ſome paces of her Chamber he found the <hi>Duenua</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſearch of the Shepherd; and being prevented by him, miſtook him for <hi>Antonine;</hi> it being then ſo dark ſhe could not diſtinguiſh them, ſo that ſhe brought him to her Lady in the manner you have heard.</p>
            <pb n="120" facs="tcp:97088:62"/>
            <p>Don <hi>Anſtin</hi> was ſo enraged, he reſolved to die or retire from Court never to appear there again. The King knew the appearances which deceived him, were enough to give him mortal diſpleaſure, unleſs he diſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus'd him. But he knew not how to do it, without giving him light into the Correſpondence between his Lady and <hi>Antonine,</hi> which would make the matter much worſe and ruin a Lady he had ſtill ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect for. He was ſorry he had not hid himſelf, that he might have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted himſelf about the adventure with the Marchioneſs, without mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Marqueſs jealous. But that which induced him to be ſo malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as not to get out of the way when ſhe bid him, was the pleaſure of being reveng'd of a Woman who had play'd the <hi>Lucrece</hi> with him, and yielded to a Shepherd: If he could have believed ſhe would have put the confidence in him to
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:97088:62"/>take their meaſures together, to diſabuſe Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> on his part, and paſs over the adventure in raillery; he had certainly gone into the Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet at firſt, or adviſed with her after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards what courſe to ſteer: but he knew her humour too well, and that ſhe would not hearken to his Propoſals. Therefore that he might not loſe his labour, or oblige peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple againſt their wills, he contented himſelf to tell the Marqueſs he had not deſign'd him any wrong: that he might believe it when he took the pains to aſſure him of it: that he had always had a great eſteem and affection for him and his Lady, and made it ſufficiently appear, that his diſguiſement was purely on the account of <hi>Dorothy,</hi> whom he would have ſurpriz'd, and not the Marchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oneſs. <q>Surprize <hi>Dorothy,</hi> anſwers the Marqueſs ſighing, in my Wives Bed!</q> he ſtopt there, which made the King laugh, who had the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:97088:63"/>to ſay a great deal more to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive him; but it ſerv'd only to render him more ſuſpitious. <q>I ſhould never have believed, Sir, ſays the Marqueſs, you would have made uſe of the pretence of an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Girl, to oppreſs me with grief and with ſhame: this proceeding is not juſt towards a Servant, who hath made it the buſineſs of his life to ſtudy your Glory, and the good of your Eſtate.</q> The King could not forbear laughing at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches, which cut Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> to the heart, being mad to ſee him take pleaſure in triumphing to his Face for the injury he had done him; ſo that he let fall ſome words which paſt the reſpect due to the King. <q>You are a little out, ſays the King calmly, but I pardon the paſſion that blinds you; you accuſe me without cauſe, you reproach me unjuſtly. Had I had deſigns up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your Wife, I had not need to
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:97088:63"/>have diſguis'd my ſelf; I might have hid my ſelf when you came in, and have choſen a better time. But I did not beſtow her upon you, to do you this unkindneſs; I keep my Word to my very Enemies, if you have reaſon to diſtruſt your Wives Vertue, inquire better who does you the wrong, and find out the myſtery before you accuſe any. All men have their failings, much more all women; and he that truſts ſo tender a Sex, and ſo capable of a Paſſion they place their Glory in, is deceived at laſt. Think of what I ſay, you may one day find it true.</q> 
               <q>Ah Sir, ſays the Marqueſs, I am but too well aſſured I am de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived; but if not by you, whom ſhould I fear in the Kingdom? is there any other my Wife would vouchſafe to turn her Head for?</q> 
               <q>You ſee this, anſwers the King, ſhewing him the Shepherds Habit, you may gueſs what it means, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:97088:64"/>I was miſtaken for another.</q> 
               <q>Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herds, Sir, replyes the Marqueſs, are for Shepherdeſſes, and I ſhall never be jealous of them. Were I aſſured of your part, I would ſtill take my Wife for the honeſteſt Woman of the Kingdom.</q> 
               <q>And I aſſure you, ſays the King, as my buſineſs was not with the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, no more was hers with me. And you are to take heed the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief you fear, if it be not already done you, come not from a party you leaſt ſuſpect.</q> The King did not deſign to ſay ſo much, but the Marqueſs forc'd him to 't by bringing <hi>Dorothy</hi> into diſcourſe. And the King being very tender of that point could not forbear ſpeaking his mind. The Marqueſs ſtood mute a while, not knowing what to think of the Shepherds Habit, on which the King grounded his ſuſpicions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, that he was taken for ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but fancy'd he meant <hi>Antonine,</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:97088:64"/>becauſe his Wife had for the Kings ſatisfaction, and almoſt againſt her will, paſt part of the Afternoon with that Shepherd in a Chamber a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. He was about to laugh at the conceit, and reſuming the diſcourſe to gain further explication, <q>Could you hope, Sir ſays he, to make me jealous of any one wears ſuch a Habit as this?</q> the King made no anſwer, letting him underſtand by his ſilence what he was to think. But the Marqueſs deſiring to be fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſatisfy'd in a point of this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, <q>What Man, adds he, of that condition durſt once look upon my Wife?</q> 
               <q>That durſt <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine,</hi> replies the King ſomewhat briskly, whom the Marchioneſs, if you muſt needs know it, vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafes to fix her Eyes upon.</q> 
               <q>If <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonine,</hi> anſwers the Marqueſs, came into my Wives Chamber, it was not on her account; and had I ſeen him ſet on her Bed, and that
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:97088:65"/>he had been with her all day, and all night, it ſhould never have bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my reſt.</q> 
               <q>I believe ſo, ſays the King, had you ſeen them in bed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, you would ſcarce believe any thing.</q> 
               <q>Sir, replies the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, I ſhould take her to be <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy;</hi> and I muſt be broad awake to believe her my Wife.</q> The King made him no anſwer, and the diſcourſe was carried on ſo far, that at laſt they promiſed one another mutual Offices of Friendſhip, and agreed to watch <hi>Antonine</hi> narrowly, and give one another intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, of all paſſages that concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either, to find out who was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. The King made the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> accepted it with a great deal of indifference, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the King had done it only to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſe him.</p>
            <p>The King no ſooner left him but he returned to his Wife, who at firſt ſight of him fell to exclaiming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:97088:65"/>that Prince, who not content to have made her Apartment the Scene of an Amorous Intrigue, came diſguiſed to ſurpriſe her when he knew ſhe was ſick a-bed, and had no help at hand, but her Voice, and her Tears. That it was an action unworthy a King, who had ſo much reaſon to know her, by the proof he had made of her virtue: But ſhe ſaw clearly enough, that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaiſance of a baſe Husband was the thing encouraged him to make a new attempt upon her honour, and they were agreed together to deſtroy her. It being impoſſible the King would have ventured co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into her Chamber, as he did, had he not known the Windows were ſhut, and no light in the room. And he could not know this but from him. The Marqueſs much troubled to hear himſelf charged with ſo much baſeneſs by his Wife, of whom he thought he had rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:97088:66"/>to complain, did all he could to juſtifie himſelf to her. But all to no purpoſe, the more he juſtified himſelf, the more guilty ſhe made him; calling him Traytor, a Man of no Honour, unworthy to poſſeſs a Lady ſo virtuous as ſhe. But all this noiſe could not keep the ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> from reſolving to have the honour to lye with her that night, for he thought her dream of the monſtrous Child boded him no good. And a Vow ſo much to the purpoſe, attended with a little indiſpoſition, which obliged his Wife to have her Chamber Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows ſhut up, and the King's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to her in a Shepherd's Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit, gave cauſe for conjectures which pointed directly to his Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head: he needed no more motive to have her abſolved that Evening of ſo delicate a Vow.</p>
            <p>He ſent preſently to pray the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Carthagene,</hi> his particular
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:97088:66"/>Friend, to do him the honour of coming to his Lodgings: the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop came, who not only abſolved the Lady from her Vow, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the duty of his Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, applyed himſelf to make Peace between the Marqueſs and his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and happily effected it to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of both.</p>
            <p>And their Union after the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop's Benediction, being greater than ever, they began to ask one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother in good earneſt, the whole truth of the ſtory. The Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was to ſpeak firſt, of common right, as having more cauſe of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint than Don <hi>Auſtin:</hi> She told him it was moſt true, that in the dark, as he had left her, ſhe heard one come in without ſaying a word, which ſurpriſed her very much: But more, when ſhe found he came and ſate on the Bed, which made her, trembling for fear, call in <hi>Alice</hi> to her aid, and that he came
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:97088:67"/>in himſelf the next moment. Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> believed all this to be true as the Goſpel, not thinking it poſſible his Wife could have the Conſcience to tell a Lye the next minute after receiving Epiſcopal Benediction. He told her on his part, the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence he had had with the King, who aſſured him, he had no other deſign but to ſurpriſe <hi>Dorothy,</hi> which in truth might be true. But the moſt pleaſant jeſt of all is, adds he, he would fain have made me jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous of <hi>Antonine.</hi> And becauſe he hath reaſon to be jealous of that Shepherd, he would have all the World be ſo too; And ſince he cannot get rid of him, he would ſet on another to do him that piece of ſervice. The Marchioneſs here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon plaid her part excellently well, making a thouſand exclamations, clapping her hands, lifting her eyes to Heaven, laughing with all her force, and doing all other Actions
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:97088:67"/>of a Woman amazed at the ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the News, which afforded them matter of diſcourſe moſt part of that Night.</p>
            <p>In the mean time, the Marqueſs according to the agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and him, to watch over <hi>Antonine,</hi> failed not at his ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to give the neceſſary orders, as to <hi>Dorothy;</hi> as for his Wives part he feared nothing. The King on the other ſide eager for the ſport, and deſirous at any rate to convince the incredulous Marqueſs, of the new Title his Wife had given him, placed his Scouts abroad to obſerve <hi>Antonine's</hi> motions towards the Marchioneſs. But ſhe was before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand with him, having that Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſent orders by the <hi>Duenna</hi> to the Shepherd to retire, and not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach the Palace, eſpecially her A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partment till notice from her. So that the Spies for ſome days could give their Maſters no account. But
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:97088:68"/>abſence is the greateſt of torments for Lovers, and the loſs of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of what you love, is little leſs then the loſs of Life. <hi>Antonine</hi> was in torment not only on the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of <hi>Dorothy,</hi> but of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs, who ſerved for a kind of amorous conſolation for him, when he could not ſee <hi>Dorothy.</hi> The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs was no leſs afflicted; and Women, as 'tis ſaid, being more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent in their paſſions than Men, 'tis credible, this Lady, who loved the Shepherd ſo well, had a very ill time on't. She had none but <hi>Alice,</hi> her Univerſal Confident to comfort her. And the poor old Wretch was as much afflicted as her Lady, to ſee her languiſh, and grow melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly: She would by all means go ſeek out <hi>Antonine,</hi> to make her chearful, promiſing the Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to bring him in ſo ſafe and ſo ſecretly, that no one ſhould know of it. But the Marchioneſs had
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:97088:68"/>more Wit than to run ſuch a ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard, and choſe rather to go ſee him at his Lodging, than expoſe him to diſcovery, by being ſurpriſed in hers. She asked the old <hi>Duenna,</hi> if ever ſhe had been at the Gardiners? and <hi>Alice</hi> having made Anſwer, ſhe was acquainted with him, and his Wife one of her beſt Friends; <q>I tell you, ſays the Marchioneſs, the reaſon of my Queſtion, and the deſign I have laid. I know your fidelity, and the affection you have always had for me, therefore I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fide in you. I will go ſee <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> at his Lodging, I take that to be the ſureſt courſe: <hi>Dorothy</hi> is much about my pitch; I will take a ſuit of hers, and I doubt not but I ſhall be taken for her, when I am ſeen go to her Fathers: we need only order things ſo, that when I am got thither, <hi>Antonine</hi> may have notice, and the Gardiner and his Wife both ſent out of the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:97088:69"/>way, for they would wonder at the viſit. This muſt be done to morrow Morning, when the Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians have preſcribed me a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for my pretended indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</q> 
               <q>The <hi>Duenna</hi> anſwered, all this would be eaſily done, that the Gardiner went at three a Clock in the Morning to work in the Garden, and ſhe would undertake to give <hi>Antonine</hi> notice of the honour intended him, and take out the Gardiner's Wife along with her a-walking till Dinner-time.</q> All this was accordingly reſolved, and executed. The <hi>Duenna</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the charge of her Ladies War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drobe, provided that Evening a Suit for the purpoſe. And at ſix in the Morning came in to awake her, telling her before Don <hi>Auſtin,</hi> that the Water was ready, and ſhe might preſently bathe her ſelf. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs who had firſt adviſed her to it, encouraged her to riſe, becauſe ſhe
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:97088:69"/>ſeemed ſomewhat loth: with much adoe ſhe took her Morning-Gown, and entred the Bathing-room, where ſhe found a Suit of <hi>Dorothie's</hi> ready for her, which ſhe put on, while the <hi>Duenna</hi> trudg'd away to <hi>Antonine</hi> to diſpoſe things there for her reception.</p>
            <p>The Scouts were night and day abroad, both the Kings and the Marqueſs's, or at leaſt had order to be ſo. But Favorites are commonly bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſerved than their Maſters: Don <hi>Auſtin</hi> was fallen aſleep again, when one of his Spies came to tell him, he ſaw <hi>Dorothy</hi> go in at her Father's. At this time of day, thinks the Marqueſs, <hi>Dorothy</hi> takes the pains to go to her Father's, there's deſign in the caſe; I muſt carry the King the News, it is worth the trouble. With that he got up in all haſte and dreſt himſelf, for fear of the birds being flown e're he could get from the King to the Gardiners. He had
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:97088:70"/>not the patience to carry his Wife the News to the Bathing-room, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to treat her with the whole ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry at his return. He got to the King's Chamber, deſired audience about urgent buſineſs, was admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and immediately fell a laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <q>You may imagine, Sir, I would not have come thus early to diſturb your Reſt, had I not a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular buſineſs to acquaint you with. The happy <hi>Antonine</hi> is this moment in the Arms of the Marchioneſs.</q> 
               <q>I am not ſurpriſed at it, ſays the King, laughing alſo, and if you had no more to tell me, you needed not to have taken the pains to be ſo early up; for I am perſwaded, they have been long a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe very well agreed.</q> 
               <q>No, no, Sir, ſays the Marqueſs in railery, I am come to tell you, according to my duty, that <hi>Dorothy</hi> is gone thus early to give her Parents a viſit, wherein you may believe <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:97088:70"/>ſhall have his ſhare.</q> 
               <q>But what, replies the King, if you have for once, taken <hi>Dorothy</hi> for the Marchioneſs:</q> 
               <q>I fear no mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, Sir, anſwers the Marqueſs, for beſides that, I left my Wife but now in her Bathing-room; the news I bring you, was told me by two of my Servants, who know <hi>Dorothy</hi> very well, and ſaw her go in at her Fathers.</q> The King ſaid not a word more, but got up and was dreſt, and would go in Perſon with the Marqueſs to the Gardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner's. They got thither in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and finding a little Girl at the door, asked who was within: She anſwered, none but <hi>Antonine</hi> and <hi>Dorothy,</hi> in a Chamber ſhe ſhewed them. What a tranſport of Fury did this put the King in, who till then feared nothing! he ran to the Chamber, and finding it ſhut, knockt at the Door, with that vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and rage, as if he would have
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:97088:71"/>ſtorm'd the beſieged: no body o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, nor anſwered; the King ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely incenſed, had no longer pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, but commanded two of his Servants to break down the door. He was obey'd, and entred in firſt, and next him Don <hi>Auſtin.</hi> But the Gallant was got out at the Window, and no body left but the fair Lady, ſitting in a corner of the Chamber; with more confuſion than fear, wrapt up in her <hi>Manto,</hi> to ſee the unhappy Cataſtrophe. The King broke out into bitter Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage againſt her, and had perhaps gone further, but that the Marqueſs minded him of his Character: However, he reſolved toput to open ſhame that little Traytreſs (as he often called her) taking her by the <hi>Manto,</hi> in which ſhe kept her ſelf muffled. At laſt he ſnatch'd it off, but who was more ſurpriſed, he, or Don <hi>Auſtin,</hi> to ſee it was the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chioneſs? The King was extreme
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:97088:71"/>glad, and ſeeing the Marqueſs thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-ſtruck, without ſpeech, or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, could not forbear laughing. <q>Now, Don <hi>Auſtin,</hi> ſays he, you ſee how people are miſtaken, is this <hi>Dorothy,</hi> or the Marchioneſs?</q> With that the enraged Husband, not able to indure the King's Raile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the inſupportable affront his virtuous Lady did him, fell upon her without reſpect to the King's Preſence, with that violence and anger, the King had much ado to get him from her. He drew him out of that Chamber, and as they went from the Gardiners, met <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonine</hi> in Cuſtody, having been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the care of the Marqueſs, who to make good his News to the King, had given order for appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending him, if he endeavoured to eſcape. The ſight of <hi>Antonine</hi> dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled his fury, and he had certainly ſtabbed him with his Poniard, had not the King, in his turn, minded
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:97088:72"/>him where he was, and of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect due to his Character.</p>
            <p>Poor <hi>Antonine</hi> was put into the Tower of <hi>Aranjuez.</hi> The King loſt no time to go ſee <hi>Dorothy,</hi> and tell her the whole Story, of which he hoped to make advantage. But the poor Innocent having with aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment heard the King, fell a-crying when ſhe underſtood <hi>Antonine</hi> was in Priſon. She fell upon her Knees, and pray'd him if he lov'd her, to ſet <hi>Antonine</hi> at liberty, and not do him any harm. The King having reproached her, for having ſo little reſentment againſt a Shepherd, guilty of ſuch falſhood to her, who in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the kindneſs ſhe had for him, had thrown himſelf into the Arms of another; told her, he could not ſet him at liberty ſo ſoon, but muſt give at leaſt ſo much ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Don <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who had cauſe to take away his Life, much more to have him kept Priſoner. <hi>Dorothy</hi>
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:97088:72"/>ſomewhat comforted by the King's promiſe to do <hi>Antonine</hi> no further harm, and mov'd on the other ſide with the reaſons ſhe was told ſhe had to be angry with her Shepherd, was not very earneſt for his Enlarge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The King finding her more complaiſant than ever, paſt part of the day with her: While they were together, the Captain of the Guard came to know his pleaſure, how <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonine</hi> ſhould be us'd. The King bid him give him what he called for, but not permit any to ſee him or ſpeak to him, except ſuch only as brought a Ring, which he took out of his Pocket, and ſhew'd the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, that he might know it. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi> having obſerv'd all this, waited an opportunity to get that Ring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her hands. By good fortune, the King having ſlept little the Night before, and been awak'd early that Morning by the Marqueſs, could not forbear falling faſt a-ſleep in <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rothy</hi>'s
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:97088:73"/>Chamber, who failed not to ſlip her Hand in his Pocket: And with a great deal of dexterity took out the Ring. The King awak'd not long after, and having ſpent ſome time with her went to Bed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dorothy</hi> was no ſooner at liberty, but ſhe went very joyfully to the Tower, where <hi>Antonine</hi> was pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner. And having ſhew'd the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer the King's Ring, entred with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out difficulty: <hi>Antonine</hi> was ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed to ſee her; ſhe fell preſently to complain of him, but the Cunning Shepherd quickly appeaſed her; And having real kindneſs for her, and ſeeing ſhe ſlighted the paſſion of a Great King for love of him, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to marry her, and not part with her till ſhe had engaged her ſelf to be his Wife, and received his engagement to be her Husband; leſt the King taking advantage of his Impriſonment (as he had reaſon to fear) ſhould rob him of her. They
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:97088:73"/>were quickly agreed, and paſt that night like Fortunate Lovers.</p>
            <p>The King ſlept ſoundly, and little dreamt of the deſigns againſt him, of which he was likely to be the more ſenſible, as the hopes of obtaining his deſires were more probable than ever, when he parted with his Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs. At his riſing they told him, a Gentleman pray'd Audience upon buſineſs of importance. The King ordered him admittance. The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman falling preſently on his knees. <q>Great Sir, ſays he, I come to beg Pardon for a Gentleman, whoſe Youth hath made him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit a fault pardonable in thoſe of riper Years.</q> 
               <q>You beg my Pardon, Friend, ſays the King, bidding him ſtand up, for a Gentleman I know no more than the Fault you have mentioned.</q> 
               <q>Sir, anſwers he, the Shepherd you committed yeſterday to Priſon is Don <hi>Alphonſo de Leon.</hi>
               </q> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Antonine,</hi> ſays the King, interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:97088:74"/>him, much ſurpriz'd at the news, Is he of the Houſe of <hi>Leon?</hi>
               </q> 
               <q>Yes, replyes the Gentleman, he is a Younger-Brother of that Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Family, who arriv'd <hi>incognito</hi> at your Court, came to take a turn at <hi>Aranjuez:</hi> And as he was walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Garden, the Maſter, as the cuſtom is, preſented him with a Noſegay by his Daughter, whom Don <hi>Alphonſo</hi> found ſo charming, he fell that moment paſſionately in love with her. We were engag'd that very day for <hi>Toledo:</hi> but he feigned himſelf indiſpos'd; and having taken no reſt that night, he look'd very ill the next Morning. We would have perſwaded him to return to <hi>Madrid,</hi> where he might have the help of able Phyſicians, rather than ſtay at a Place where he could ſcarce have one pittiful Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon to let him Blood. For three or four days he obſtinately inſiſted, the Air at <hi>Aranjuez</hi> would be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:97088:74"/>to recover him. And that he ſhould not want Phyſician or Chyrurgeon. In the mean time he could neither eat nor ſleep; he was ſo tormented with his Love, which was his only Diſtemper, and at length much prejudiced his health. But fearing the buſineſs would at laſt come to light, and having ever had confidence in me, who am his Governour, he took me one day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide to acquaint me with the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret, praying me, if I lov'd him, I would be ſo kind to him, as to find out the means to ſtay ſome time at <hi>Aranjuez.</hi> I omitted nothing that could be ſaid to divert him from the purſuit of ſo extravagant a Paſſion. I repreſented to him a thouſand in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences would attend it; I minded him of the Glory of his Birth, and the blemiſh it would be to him to amuſe himſelf with an Engagement ſo much beneath him: and at laſt threatned to write of it
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:97088:75"/>to his Parents. But all to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. He fell down at my feet, begg'd of me upon his knees and with tears in his Eyes, that for a Month or two I would permit him to pleaſe himſelf in his folly, ſwear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he would die or kill himſelf, if I forced him from <hi>Aranjuez.</hi> I knew not what to do; I was almoſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted, and wiſht I had never been concern'd with him. At laſt, after long reſiſtance, I yielded to his prayers and tears, and conſented to one Months ſtay at <hi>Aranjuez;</hi> and that he ſhould play what part he pleaſed there, but not under the Name or Character of what he really was; leaſt, if that came to be known, it might prove an inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible ſtain to him and to me. The fifth day we left <hi>Aranjuez,</hi> with deſign, according to my Promiſe, to return both together in a very ſhort time. We went to <hi>Toledo,</hi> and having ſent away all our
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:97088:75"/>People to wait our coming at <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dova,</hi> in the way to <hi>Sevile,</hi> where we deſigned to go; we bought us two Habits of Shepherds, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned to <hi>Aranjuez.</hi> Our deſign was to ſend him to the Gardiner's to live with him, and offer him very good terms, in hopes he would not know him in that diſguiſe. In our way to <hi>Aranjuez</hi> we lay at an Inn, within two leagues of this Place, where the Hoſt was a friend of the Gardiner's, and very ready to ſerve us, after a ſmall preſent I made him. This Man recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him under the Name of <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine,</hi> the Son of a Rich Shepherd near <hi>Toledo,</hi> who deſired to have his Son kept at ſome diſtance from him, and offer'd a very good al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance for his maintenance. <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> was very well received by the Gardiner. I ſtay'd at that Inn, and came two or three times a-week to ſee the young Shepherd, but could
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:97088:76"/>never prevail with him to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, putting me off ſtill from one Month to another; till yeſterday in the evening, the Gardiner ſent me an Expreſs to bring me the news of his misfortune. I will not trouble your Majeſty with the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe and grief it put me to, I ſtay'd no longer than while. I could put off my diſguiſe, as no longer uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful; and reſume my former Habit, and came immediately away to the Gardiner's laſt night, where I was told all the paſſages.</q>
            </p>
            <p>The King no leſs charm'd than aſtoniſht at the circumſtances of this Story, reſolved to do Juſtice to the prejudice of his Affections; and to declare that Don <hi>Alphonſo de Leon,</hi> whoſe paſſion was ſo ſtrong and ſo tender, deſerv'd better than he to enjoy the fair <hi>Dorothy;</hi> he took the reſolution from that moment not to croſs him in his Amour. He got himſelf dreſt to go carry the news to
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:97088:76"/>that Charming Maid, and to give her full liberty to diſpoſe of her Heart as ſhe pleaſed; thinking him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf obliged by ſuch a Sacrifice, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pair all the trouble and injury he had done that young Gentleman. But he was ſtrangely aſtoniſht; when, coming to <hi>Dorothy</hi>'s Chamber, he was told ſhe lay not there that night; and that they knew not what was become of her.</p>
            <p>He thought firſt ſhe was gone to ſee <hi>Antonine;</hi> but then finding little reaſon for that, he fancied ſhe was gone to her Father's, but could not gueſs for what end. Yet the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie he was not yet rid of, for all his reſolution againſt it, had made that impreſſion within him. It perſwaded him againſt all appearance his firſt thoughts were true, and that ſhe was certainly gone to <hi>Antonine:</hi> And to ſatisfie himſelf, he muſt go to the Priſon to know the news.
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:97088:77"/>He asked the Officer, who had been to ſee the Shepherd: He told him, Not any but the Marchioneſs's Maid, (ſo they called <hi>Dorothy</hi>) who had been all Night with him, and was there ſtill. The King redden'd to hear him, and asked him in ſome heat, if he had not given him or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der no body ſhould ſee the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd? Except thoſe, Sir, anſwers the Officer, who ſhould ſhew me your Signet, which that Maid brought me. My Signet, ſays the King, putting his Hand in his Pock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et: he found it was gone. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing highly offended with the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the little Laſſe, he went into the Priſon to complain of her, where he ſaw the two tender Lovers, falling preſently at his feet. <hi>Antonine</hi> was the Speaker, and begg'd the King's Pardon, for two Loving Youths, who placing all their happineſs in the Enjoyment of each other, had united by indiſſoluble Bonds, what Love
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:97088:77"/>had already ſtrongly chained toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <q>
               <p>You ſhould not (anſwers the King, making them both ſtand up) by deſiring my Pardon, have robb'd me of the the glory I deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelf, by preventing your Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition with my Bounty: I am not come hither as a Rival jealous of your Happineſs, to croſs your Love any more; but I come as a Prince to do Juſtice to the moſt tender Paſſion in the World, which, (how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it trouble me) I muſt own to have charm'd me.</p>
               <p>You ſhall be married, Don <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo,</hi> adds he, embracing him, and I ſhall be very ſorry (having the eſteem I have for <hi>Dorothy</hi>) to hinder her good Fortune.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> hearing theſe laſt words, could no longer doubt, but the King had been fully informed who he was: and falling the ſecond time on his knees, would have excuſed what his exceſs of love made him do.
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:97088:78"/>The King embracing him again, anſwered, <q>He could not condemn a paſſion himſelf had been ſubject to; that the Beauty and merit of <hi>Dorothy</hi> deſerved better fortune than her Birth promiſed her. That it was no news to ſee (not Genle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, but) Princes to chooſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorts out of Cottages: That Love wrought far greater miracles: and as for Birth, it was no obſtacle in their Caſe, who are in a condition to beſtow Honours, and Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities.</q>
            </p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe was received with thanks and acknowledgments, from Don <hi>Alphonſo</hi> and <hi>Dorothy.</hi> After which the King having ſent for rich Cloaths for the one, and the other, he led them to the Palace, where he was pleaſed to have their Nupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als celebrated, with all the ſplendour and Magnificence due to the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Gentleman of the Ancient and Illuſtrious Family of <hi>Leon.</hi> The
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:97088:78"/>King Honoured <hi>Dorothie's</hi> Parents with Titles of Nobility, and made her Father Governour of <hi>Aranjuez.</hi> The poor Marchioneſs was put into a Nunnery, and after two years pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, her Husband who notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the accident at <hi>Aranjuez,</hi> had a love for her ſtill, ſet her at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, and took her home to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, where they liv'd the reſt of their days in a fair correſpondence, if you conſider with how much reaſon they had been parted.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:97088:79"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books Printed for</hi> J. Magnes, <hi>and</hi> R. Bentley <hi>in</hi> Ruſſel-ſtreet, <hi>in</hi> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent-Garden.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>PLAYS.</head>
               <p>TArtuff, or the French Puritan, a Comedy, written in French by the famed Wit of <hi>France,</hi> Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Moliere,</hi> and made Engliſh by Mr. <hi>M. Medburne.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Plays written by Madam <hi>Behn.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Forc'd Marriage, or the Jealous Bridegroom.</p>
                  <p>Abdelazar, or the Moor's Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge.</p>
                  <p>The Town Fop, or Sir Timothy Taudry.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Plays written by Mr. <hi>Howard.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>All Miſtaken: or, the Mad Couple.</p>
                  <p>The Engliſh Monſieur.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97088:79"/>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Plays written by Mr. <hi>Crown.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caliſto,</hi> or the Chaſt Nymph, a Maſque Acted at the Court.</p>
                  <p>The Countrey Wit.</p>
                  <p>The Deſtruction of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> by <hi>Titus Veſpatian.</hi> In two Parts.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Andromache,</hi> a Tragedy.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>Plays written by Mr. <hi>Lee.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The Tragedy of <hi>Nero.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sophonisba,</hi> or <hi>Hannibat</hi>'s Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gloriana,</hi> or the Court of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Rival Queens, or the Death of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great.</p>
                  <p>The Plain Dealer, written by Mr. <hi>Wicherly.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Miſtaken Husband, part of it written by <hi>John Dryden,</hi> Eſq;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dryden</hi>'s Notes of <hi>Morocco.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Madam Fickle, or the Witty Falſe One, written by Mr. <hi>Durſey.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Fond Husband, or the Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Siſters, by Mr. <hi>Durſey.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Generous Enemies.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:97088:80"/>
               <head>Some Engſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Novels.</head>
               <p>Happy Slave, in Three Parts Compleat.</p>
               <p>Count <hi>Brion:</hi> or, the Cheating Gallant.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zelinda,</hi> a Romance, by Monſieur <hi>Sidery</hi> in 12.</p>
               <p>Covent Garden Drollery, in 8.</p>
               <p>The Diſorders of Love, in 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mayer</hi>'s Letters.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Some Books of Devotion.</head>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Andrews</hi> Devotions.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Hatten</hi>'s Pſalter in 12.</p>
               <p>Moral Eſſays, on many Importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Duties in 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas</hi> a <hi>Kempis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lipſions of Conſtancy.</p>
               <p>The Education of a Prince in 12.</p>
               <p>The Triumphs of Love, over Fortune, a Novel.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:97088:80"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
